<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian sacrament and sacrifice by way of discourse, meditation, &amp; prayer upon the nature, parts, and blessings of the holy communion / by Dan. Brevint.</title>
            <author>Brevint, Daniel, 1616-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23806</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07911553</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07911553</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40360</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29341)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40360)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1198:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian sacrament and sacrifice by way of discourse, meditation, &amp; prayer upon the nature, parts, and blessings of the holy communion / by Dan. Brevint.</title>
                  <author>Brevint, Daniel, 1616-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 129, [2] p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At the Theater in Oxford,</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Anglican Communion.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Church of England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40360:1"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIAN Sacrament and Sacrifice By way of Diſcourſe, MEDITATION, &amp; PRAYER Upon THE NATURE, PARTS, and Bleſſings OF THE Holy Communion.</p>
            <p>By DAN. BREVINT. D. D</p>
            <p>At the THEATER in OXFORD, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:40360:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40360:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The CHRISTIAN SACRAMENT &amp; Sacrifice.</head>
                  <p>At the THEATER in OXFORD</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40360:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40360:3"/>
            <head>To The RIGHT HONOURABLE The Lady ELIZABETH CARTERET.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is one of the many Tracts which I made at Paris on ſeveral Subjects, at the inſtance of thoſe two Incomparable Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, who there for many years continually emploied me in their ſervice. What uſe they were pleaſed to make of them, your Ladyſhip knows beſt, being often admitted with
<pb facs="tcp:40360:4"/>ſome other Perſons of Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to their privat Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Therefore when I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with theſe Papers, I but repeat and ratify their gift, and by this public Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs pay that reſpect which I owe (beſides what is due up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other accounts) to that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Eſteem and Kindneſs which they ever had for your Ladiſhip.</p>
            <p>Thoſe great and holy Souls had no deſire, more earneſt then to contemplate and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Chriſtian religion in its
<pb facs="tcp:40360:4"/>original beauty, &amp; ſee it freed from the Encombrance which ordinary Controverſies most commonly throw upon it. And really tho they did under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all theſe Scholastic points as well or better then their Teachers, (eſpecially the Princeſs of <hi>Turenne,</hi> whoſe clear and quick Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, and neat and unar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial eloquence were won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful) yet they cared ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for them, that they deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red very often the unhappy neceſſity that had filled the
<pb facs="tcp:40360:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:40360:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:40360:6"/>Church with ſuch weapons; and had ſo flanck't about (to uſe here their expreſſion) Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem with Baſtions, that one could hardly ſee the Temple.</p>
            <p>I can aſſure you Madam, that upon this account the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communion which is as the tree of life in the Paradiſe of God, the moſt generous plant in his Vineyard of the Church, hath bin the worſt dealt with. For as it was moſt deſpiteful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treated by Popery; the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants did ſpend moſt of their care this way to ſecure it,
<pb facs="tcp:40360:6"/>whereby it could not be well expected that men thus taken up in raiſing fences, in plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thorns and quicksets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt wild Bores, could have much time to dreſs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove better plants. Then came from Germany Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, and from other parts Socinians, who pretend that the best way of pruning lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xuriant excreſcencies, is to cut up by the roots.</p>
            <p>Here then Madam, while the Romaniſts having made havock of the Vineyard, and
<pb facs="tcp:40360:7"/>laid it waſt; the fatneſs of the ground brought forth that poiſonous wild vine of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-Maſs: and others left nothing but dead ſapleſs branches and dry leaves, the emty figures of fanatic Heretics; I make it my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to reſcue it out of the hands of ſuch Husbandmen, and to reſtore all back again both to the full meaning and inſtitution of Chriſt, who is the Planter as well as the Maſter of the Vineyard, and to the Practice of the Holy
<pb facs="tcp:40360:7"/>Fathers, who for ſeveral hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of years, dreſſed it, and made it bear excellent fruit. So here I take no more notice of either Papiſts or Sectaries, no nor Proteſtants neither, then as if the former had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver appeared in the world to trouble and ſpoil the Church of God, nor the latter to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert and redreſs it.</p>
            <p>The holy Sacrament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus ſet at liberty, and enlarged to its full extent, will appear preſently atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with all its Duties and
<pb facs="tcp:40360:8"/>Bleſſings, as the Ladder of Jacob did, with aſcending and deſcending Angels. This may be ſoon perceived, by any one who will but take the trouble to read this Book, ſo he do it with ſome attention, and diſtinctly in parcels; a caution which I deſire may be adverted to. Chronicles, or eloquent Diſcourſes, may beſt pleaſe, when they are curſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily run over. But Myſteries must be ſtudied, or they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be well underſtood; and God knows how much more is
<pb facs="tcp:40360:8"/>here required at our hands beſides bare underſtanding. Therefore I have added to the Diſcours that refers to the advancing the mind in knowledg, Meditation and Prayer, the two uſual atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants on devotion; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joined together, are the only probable means of deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuccesfully with holy things, and of attaining by the uſe, to the true end of this Sacrament, which aims at nothing leſs then a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Communion between us
<pb facs="tcp:40360:9"/>and Chriſt, even here on earth while we ſeem to be abſent from him: and withall at ſuch a reciprocal correſpondency between God and his Church, as may both open our hearts toward him in holy Duties and Performances, and open his hand and bowels toward us in all neceſſary Mercies.</p>
            <p>I know Madam that for the confirming of all this, I need but appeal to your own experience. And tis part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on this account, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as asking leave, I
<pb facs="tcp:40360:9"/>have made bold to put your Name before this Book: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it having bin firſt writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for the peculiar uſe of two Perſons, whom God had ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifyed in all reſpects much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the rate of theſe Times; it ſeems to claim a ſpecial Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to their acceptation and reading, who intimately knew the worth of thoſe Princeſſes, and walk after their ſteps, at ſo neer a diſtance as your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip doth, to whom I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM</salute> 
               <signed>A moſt Humble and Faithful Servant, DAN. BREVINT.</signed> 
               <dateline>Durham <date>Jan. 24. 1673.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:40360:10"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40360:10"/>
            <head>THE CHRISTIAN SACRAMENT <hi>and Sacrifice.</hi> By way of Diſcourſe, MEDITATION, and PRAYER, upon THE NATURE, PARTS, and Bleſſings Of the Holy Communion.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Importance of well underſtanding the Nature of this Sacrament.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Sacrament inſtituted by Chriſt at the eve of his Paſſion, which <hi>S. Paul</hi> calls the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controverſie one of the greateſt Myſteries of Godlineſs, and the moſt ſolemn Feſtival of the Chriſtian Religion. The holy Table, or Altar, which preſents this ſacred Banquet, may, as well as the old Tabernacle, take to it ſelf the title of * <hi>Meeting:</hi> ſince there the People muſt appear to Worship God, and there certainly God is preſent to <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tabernacle for appointed time &amp; meeting.</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:40360:11"/>meet and to bleſs his People. At the Place, and during the whole Act of this <hi>Meeting</hi> with God, the Chriſtian Communicants are in a ſpecial manner invited to offer up to God their Souls, their Bodies, their Goods, their Vows, their Praiſes, and whatſoever they can <hi>give:</hi> and God on the other ſide offers to us the Body and Blood of his Son, and all thoſe other Bleſſings withal, that will aſſuredly follow this ſacred Gift. For this muſt be granted, then the holy Communion is not only a <hi>Sacrament</hi> that the Worshipper is to come to for no other purpoſe, then to <hi>receive;</hi> nor a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> only, where he should have nothing els to do, but to <hi>give:</hi> but it is as the great Solemnity of the ancient Paſsover was, whereof it hath taken the place; a great Myſtery conſiſting both of <hi>Sacrament</hi> and <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> that is, of the Religious Service, which the People owe to God, and of the full <hi>Salvation,</hi> which God is pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to promiſe his People.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It may by this appear, how far it concerns every Chriſtian not to err in a Point, that makes the Center both of his <hi>Happineſs</hi> and his <hi>Duty:</hi> and that ties the very knot, which in a manner joins Man with God. It was upon this account that the Devil, who bore ever
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40360:11"/>an equal hatred both to what is Holy to God, and to all what is conducible to the Salvation of Man, hath from the very beginning bin buſie with this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: and hath ever ſince given the Church more trouble about the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, then ever the Angel ſuffered about the Body of Moſes. <hi>Jude</hi> 9. For the Body of Chriſt, as the Holy Fathers diſtinguish it, being of two ſorts, to wit the <hi>Natural,</hi> which is in Heaven, and the <hi>Sacramental,</hi> which is bleſſed and given at the holy Table; the primitive Heretics, whom the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Antichriſt ſet up and animated againſt the Church, ſpent all their ſtrength and their venim, at the very time, and in the face of the Apoſtles, in order to deſtroy the firſt, which is the Human Nature of Chriſt, and to reduce it to a <hi>Phantoſm:</hi> and God knows whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſecond, that is the <hi>Sacramental,</hi> receives at this day any better enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment from two contrary Parties, who make it either a <hi>falſe God,</hi> or an <hi>emty Ceremony.</hi> Of all theſe oppoſite Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the firſt, who aſſaulted his Flesh, could in this impiety be but poor vain undertakers, this glorious Body being highly exalted above their reach: but the ſecond are on this account more dangerous, becauſe the bleſſed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40360:12"/>which makes up this other Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, may daily fall into the hands of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> or a <hi>profane</hi> Abuſer. Therefore it very much concerns them, whoſoever have either any Piety towards God, or any care of their own Souls, to menage their Devotions with ſuch precaution and judgment, that this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Sacrament may be kept ſafe from the attemts of ſuperſtition and profaneneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECTION II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning the Sacrament, as it is a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of the Sufferings and Death of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THe bleſſed Communion was chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtituted by the Son of God, for a <hi>Sacrament</hi> in the Church: But when it is received by the Chriſtian People, if this <hi>receiving</hi> of theirs be right, it muſt needs be attended with the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch other Performances, as will make it alſo a <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> As it is a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, this great Myſtery shews three Faces, looking directly towards three Times, and offering to all worthy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers three ſorts of incomparable Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; that of <hi>Repreſenting</hi> the true <hi>Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy</hi> of Chriſts Sufferings, which are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40360:12"/>paſt, whereof it is a <hi>Memorial:</hi> that of <hi>exhibiting</hi> the firſt Fruits of theſe Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in real and <hi>preſent Graces,</hi> whereof it is a moral <hi>Conveyance</hi> and <hi>Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> and that of <hi>aſſuring</hi> Men of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Graces, and Glories <hi>to come,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it is an infallible <hi>Pledg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. As this Sacrament looks back; it is an authentic <hi>Memorial,</hi> which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior hath left in his Church, of what He was pleaſed to ſuffer for Her. For tho theſe Sufferings of His were both ſo dreadful and Holy, as to make the Heavens mourn, the Earth quake, and all men tremble: yet becauſe great Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, how terrible and magnificent ſoever they be, whilſt they laſt, are not leſs, then the ſmalleſt things, apt to be forgotten when they are gon: and ſo, there was ſmall likelyhood; that the Paſſion of Jeſus Chriſt, which was not ſeen upon the Croſs above the ſpace of ſome few hours, could be well preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the memory of men throughout all ages; therefore our Saviour was pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at his laſt Supper to ordain this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, as a holy <hi>Memorial, Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>Image,</hi> of what He was about to ſuffer for that short time, to ſave his dear Church for ever. So that when Chriſtian Poſterity, which had not ſeen the Crucifixion of their Savior, like the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40360:13"/>young Iſraelites, that had not ſeen the killing of the firſt Paſsover, should come to ask after the ſignification of thoſe things, this <hi>Bread,</hi> this <hi>Wine,</hi> the <hi>Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the one, the <hi>powring</hi> out of the other, and the <hi>Participation</hi> of both; this ſacred Myſtery might expoſe to faithful Beholders as a preſent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Object, both the <hi>Martyrdom</hi> and the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of this crucified Savior, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his <hi>Flesh,</hi> shedding his <hi>Blood,</hi> and pouring out his very <hi>Soul</hi> for the expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Sins.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Therefore, as in the Feaſts of the Paſsover, the late Jews could ſay, <hi>This is the Lamb, theſe are the Herbs, and this is the Bread of affliction, which our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did eat in Egypt;</hi> becauſe their lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Feaſts did ſo effectually repreſent the former; that the People, who did par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of thoſe, had ground enough both to act and to ſpeak as if they had bin preſent at this: So at our holy <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> which ſucceeds the Paſsover, and is undoubtedly no leſs a bleſſed, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Sacrament to ſet before our eyes <hi>Chriſt our Paſsover who is ſacrificed for us,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.7. <hi>Our Saviour,</hi> ſays <hi>St. Auguſtin, doubted not to ſay, This is my Body, when he gave to his Diſciples the Figure of his Body.</hi> Becauſe eſpecially, beſides the <hi>Commemoration,</hi> this Sacrament duly given,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40360:13"/>and faithfully received, makes the Thing which it repreſents as really preſent for our uſe, and as really powerful in order to our Salvation, as if the Thing it ſelf were newly done or in doing. <hi>Eating this Bread and drinking of this Cup you ſet forth the death of the Lord.</hi> 1 Cor. 11.26.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For certainly, not to miſtake the meaning of Chriſt, nor to injure his Myſtery; whenſoever with the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church we call it a <hi>Memorial,</hi> or a <hi>Figure;</hi> great care muſt be taken leſt we confound theſe Venerable Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which God himſelf hath ſet up in his Church, and for his Church, with thoſe emty Figures and Marks which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome old Tradition, or ſome private phanſie may by chance have put in our way. Men of ordinary Underſtanding do not regard with the ſame eye the Armes and Images of Princes, which public Autority hath ſet up in a public emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Place: and which a Painter, to pleaſe his phanſie, hath fixt in a private Room. Without all doubt a wiſe Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler would be much more moved at the ſight of the <hi>Salt Pillar,</hi> (if it did ſtand yet where it did) which God had ſet up purpoſely, where Lots wife lookt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Sodom, then at ſome Prints of her Feet (if they were to be ſeen yet) when ſhe turned ſome other way.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40360:14"/>And if we credit the Hiſtory, that Croſs, which the firſt Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror is reported once to have ſeen in the Air (which undoubtedly the hand of God, or an Angel had made appear with ſome Deſign) could not but cauſe a greater reſpect, then that ordinary Sign of the Croſs, which Chriſtians have uſed on common occaſions. Add what no body can deny, that all Sorts of <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Monuments</hi> become more or leſs Venerable according to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or leſſer worth of the Objects, which they are made to repreſent. It had bin hard for Abraham, or for any devout Patriarck, not to feel ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Reverence and holy Fear, when they did chance to paſs again by <hi>Mamre,</hi> or by <hi>Morijah,</hi> or ſuch other remarkable Places where God had appeared to them: and who doubts but the very ſight of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> of the Mount of <hi>Olives,</hi> of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vary,</hi> &amp;c. which Chriſt honored with his Preſence when he was born, when he ſuffered, and when he went up to Heaven, did heat the primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans with conſiderable Flames of Zeal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that uſuall <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Knowledg,</hi> which they had got by their reading? But when theſe Signs and Monuments, beſides their ordinary uſe, bear with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al as it were on their Face the glorious
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40360:14"/>Character of their Inſtitution from above, and with this Inſtitution the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Deſign that God hath thereby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive in a manner, and to expoſe as full to all our ſenſes, his Paſſion and ſufferings, as if they had ſtill there true Being (as they have ſtill the ſame vertue;) a diſcreet and pious Beholder muſt needs look on theſe Ordinances with theſe three de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Devotion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The firſt is, when he conſiders thoſe great and dreadful Paſſages which this Sacrament ſets before him. I doe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve on this Altar ſome what very like the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> and Paſſion of my Savior. For thus the <hi>Bread of life</hi> was broken: thus the <hi>Lamb of God</hi> was ſlain: thus his moſt precious <hi>Blood</hi> was shed. And when I look upon the Miniſter, who by ſpeciall order from God his Maſter diſtributes this <hi>Bread</hi> and this <hi>wine,</hi> I conceive that thus verily God himſelf hath both given once his Son to dye, and gives ſtill the virtue of his Death to bleſs and to ſave every Soul that comes unfaignedly to him.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The ſecond is an Act of Adoration and Reverence, when he looks upon that good Hand, that hath conſecrated for the uſe of the Church the <hi>Memorial</hi> of theſe great Things. I cannot without ſome degree of devotion look on any Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40360:15"/>that in any wiſe puts me in mind of the Sufferings of my Savior: and if I did perceive but any Cloud, ſomewhat like them, altho it were but caſual, I would not neglect the Accident that had cauſed that Reſemblance. But ſince the good hand of my God hath purpoſely contrived it thus, to ſet before me what I ſee; and ſince by his ſpecial Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment theſe Repreſentatives are brought in hither for this Church, and among all the reſt for me: I muſt mind what Iſrael did, when the Cloud filled the Tabernacle. I will not fail to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God, aſſoon as I perceive theſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and <hi>Goſpel-Clouds</hi> appearing in the <hi>Sanctuary.</hi> Here I worship neither <hi>Sacrament,</hi> nor <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> but I will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the manner, that <hi>Moſes, David,</hi> and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> have taught me to receive poor Elements with, after the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God hath once raiſed them to the eſtate of great Myſteries. Neither the Ark nor any Clouds were ever ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Iſrael, tho ſome brutish Heathen ſometimes thought ſo: but ſure it is, the Ark was conſidered quite otherwiſe then a <hi>Cheſt,</hi> and the Cloud then a Vapor, aſſoon as God had hallowed them both, to be the Signs of his preſence. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the former People did never ſee the Temple or the Cloud, but that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40360:15"/>preſently at that ſight they uſed to throw themſelves on their faces; I will never behold theſe better and ſurer Sacraments of the glorious Mercies of God, but as ſoon as I ſee them uſed in the Church to that holy purpoſe that Chriſt hath conſecrated them to, I will not fail both to remember my Savior who conſecrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe Sacraments, and to worship alſo my Savior whom theſe Sacraments do repreſent. And God forbid, that, when I am able, I should not receive them, as my Savior himſelf was pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his own Baptiſm, with Devotion and <hi>Prayer.</hi> Luk. 3.21.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The third, which is the Crown and the compleating of the two other, is ſuch a vigorous and intenſe Act of Faith, as may correſpond to the great End, which our Savior aimed at, when He inſtituted this Sacrament. The main Intention of Chriſt was not here to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a bare <hi>Image</hi> of his Paſſion once ſuffered in order to a bare <hi>Remembrance:</hi> but over and above to enrich this <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial</hi> with ſuch an effectual and real Preſence of continuing Atonement, and ſtrength, as may both <hi>evidently ſet forth Chriſt himſelf crucified before our eyes, Gal.</hi> 3.1. and invite us to his Sacrifice, not as done and gone many years ſince, but, as to expiating grace and mercy, ſtill
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40360:16"/>laſting, ſtill new, ſtill the ſame that it was, when it was firſt offered for us.</p>
               <p n="8">8. All thoſe Sacrifices under the Law, which had both their uſe and their ſtrength limited, ſome to a year, ſome to a Month, ſome to a day, were not leſs powerful at the laſt, then they were at the firſt moment of their proper Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: and they who lived or dyed within the twelfth month of the year, after the <hi>Feaſt of Propitiations,</hi> had as much benefit from that anniverſary Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, as they, who were upon the place and at the very day, when the high Prieſt did offer it. Upon the like, but infinitly better reaſon, the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Jeſus Chriſt being appointed by God the Father for a Propitiation that should continue throughout all Ages, to the Worlds end: and withal being ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting by the Priviledg of its own <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> which is <hi>an unchangeable Prieſthood,</hi> Heb. 7.24. and by his worth, who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered it, that is the Bleſſed Son of God, and by the Power of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> by whom it was offered, which is the <hi>eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> Hebr. 9.14. all kinds of Eternity thus concurring together to the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice upon the Croſs, it muſt in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects ſtand everlaſting and Eternal, and <hi>the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever.</hi> Hebr. 13.8.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:40360:16"/> 9. Therefore this Sacrifice being ſuch, the holy Communion is ordained of Chriſt, to ſet it out to us as ſuch, that is, as effectual now at this holy <hi>Table,</hi> as it was then at the very Croſs: and by the ſame proportion the Act of worthy Receivers, (beſides Remembrance and Worship) muſt needs be this; firſt to elevate their Faith, and ſtretch their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Souls up to the <hi>Mount,</hi> with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin, who ſtood neareſt the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, or at the leaſt with the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, who lookt on it at ſome diſtance: and then look up to the <hi>Victim,</hi> to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the Everlaſting Mediator of the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant,</hi> and to the <hi>Blood of ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that ſpeaks yet,</hi> and craves for <hi>better things</hi> (Pardon and Bleſſing) <hi>then Abels did.</hi> Hebr. 12.24. Here Faith muſt be as true a <hi>ſubſiſtence</hi> of thoſe things paſt, which we <hi>believe,</hi> as 'tis of thoſe other things yet to come, which we <hi>hope</hi> for. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1.</p>
               <p n="10">10. At the approach therefore of this great <hi>Myſtery,</hi> and by the help of this ſtrong <hi>Faith,</hi> the worthy Communicant being proſtrated at the Lords Table, as at the very foot of his Croſs, shall with earneſt ſorrow confeſs and lament all his Sins, which were the nails and ſpears that pierced our Savior. We our ſelves moſt chiefly, not Pilate, nor the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40360:17"/>Jewes (for he would not have dyed for ſuch alone) <hi>we have crucifyed that Juſt one. Men and Brethren what shall we do!</hi> Act. 2.37. He shall fall amazed at that Stroke of Divine Juſtice, that being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended but by <hi>Men,</hi> could not be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, nor appeaſed but by the ſufferings and death of <hi>God. How dreadful is this Place!</hi> how deep and holy is this Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry! Then he will fall again to worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, not leſs amazed at, then thankful for, thoſe inconceavable Mercies of God the Father, who ſo gave up his only Son, and for the Mercies of God the Son, who thus gave himſelf up for us.</p>
               <p n="11">11. My Lord! and my God! <hi>I behold here in this Bread made of a Substance that was cut down, beaten, ground and bruiſed by men, all the heavy Blows and Plagues and Pains, which my Savior did ſuffer from the hands of his Murtherers: I behold in this Bread dryed up, and baked and burnt at the Fire, the fiery wrath alſo, which he ſuffered for me
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40360:17"/>from above, and from the hand of his own Father. My God, my God, why haſt thou thus for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken him! the violence of wicked men firſt hath made him a</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, <hi>then the Fire of Heaven hath made him a</hi> Burnt ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: <hi>and under both theſe Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, lo he is become to me the</hi> Bread of Life!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let us then go, to take and eat it. For tho the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that bruiſed him be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to pieces, and the direful Flames that burned him be quite put out, yet this Bread, which is the Body of the Lord, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues new. The Spears and Swords that ſlew, and the Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that compleated the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, are many years ſince ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and ſpent; but the strength and ſweet ſmell of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40360:18"/>Oblation is ſtill fragrant, the Blood ſtill warm, the words ſtill fresh, and</hi> the Lamb ſtill ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as ſlain.
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Any other Bread by duration will alter, and any other Sacrifice will loſe its ſtrength; but Thou moſt Eternal victime, offered up to God through the Eternal Spirit, by an everlaſting Prieſt, and by an Order which can never be changed, Thou remaineſt alwaies the ſame: and as thy years shall never fail, they shall never loſe nor abate any thing of thy ſaving ſtrength and</hi> mercy: <hi>help O help me alſo, that they abate nothing of my Faith. Help me to grieve for the ſenſe of my ſins, and for that of thy pains, as thoſe good Souls did, who ſaw thee ſuffer.</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 23.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Let not my heart burn with leſs Zeal
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40360:18"/>to follow and ſerve thee now, when this Bread is broken at this</hi> Table, <hi>then did the hearts of thy Diſciples, when thou didſt break it in</hi> Emaus.
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 24.32.</note> 
                  <hi>O Rock of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael. Rock of Salvation, Rock ſtruck and cleft for me, let thoſe two ſtreams of</hi> Blood, <hi>and</hi> Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>which once gushed out of thy ſide,</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.34.</note> 
                  <hi>when the Curſe of the Law, and the Rod of Moſes had opened it, bring down with them</hi> Salvation <hi>and</hi> Holineſs <hi>into my Soul, tho far diſtant from the Mountain, where thou didſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that deadly Blow. And let not my Soul leſs thirst after them at this diſtance, then if</hi> I <hi>ſtood upon</hi> Horeb, <hi>whence ſprung</hi> this water, <hi>and near the very</hi> Cleft <hi>of that Rock, the very Wounds of my Savior
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40360:19"/>whence gushed out this Sacred</hi> Blood. <hi>All the diſtance of Times and Countries, how great ſoever, which is between Adam and me, doth not keep his Sin or his Punishment any more from purſuing and reaching me, then if</hi> I <hi>had bin born in his houſe: and notwithſtanding this diſtance we ſin and dye after his</hi> Image, <hi>as if we were immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly ſprung from his</hi> Loines. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Adam, Adam deſcended pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful from above, let thy Blood reach as far, and come as freely both to ſave and to ſanctify, as the Blood of my firſt Father did both to destroy and defile me. Bleſſed Jeſu, who reviveſt by this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament the Memory of thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, quicken and ſtrengthen my faith alſo, diſpoſe my mind, prepare my heart, and then bleſs
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40360:19"/>this thine</hi> Ordinance. <hi>If</hi> I but touch <hi>(in that manner I ought to do)</hi> the Hem of his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>the Garment of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, virtue will proceed out of Him, it shall be done accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my Faith: and my poor Soul shall be made whole. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECTION. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the bleſſed Sacrament, as it ſtands for a Sign of preſent Graces.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THe ſecond Face of the bleſſed Communion looks towards <hi>the preſent Graces</hi> that attend the right uſe of it, firſt as a <hi>Figure,</hi> whereby God repreſents, ſecondly as a moral <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> whereby he is pleaſed to convey, them unto the Church. Firſt I ſay it marks and ſignifies theſe preſent Graces. For being of its own nature a Sacrament, that is, a <hi>ſign of an Inviſible Grace,</hi> it muſt principally ſtand to ſignify, and lead us to greater Bleſſings.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:40360:20"/> 2. It is the ordinary way of God, when He either promiſes or beſtowes on men any conſiderable Bleſſing, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm his <hi>word</hi> and <hi>his Gift</hi> with the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome Signs. For this I need not to alledg other Evidences then the <hi>Rainbow,</hi> the <hi>Burning Bush,</hi> Abrahams <hi>Furnace,</hi> Gideons <hi>Fleece,</hi> the <hi>Cloud,</hi> the <hi>Ark,</hi> &amp;c. which for thoſe times were Sacraments of great Things. God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſent no Prophets, without giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them as it were a Sacramental E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quippage, which could repreſent in ſome degree the <hi>Meſſage</hi> they had to deliver; witneſs the Hairy <hi>Mantels,</hi> the rent <hi>Garments,</hi> the Iron <hi>Yoakes,</hi> the <hi>Hornes,</hi> ſome times ſome kinds of <hi>life</hi> or <hi>Geſture,</hi> wherein men might <hi>ſee</hi> before hand, the Charges and ſad Predictions which they were to hear ſoon after. Our Savior did obſerve this ſame method, when he laid his hands on Children, when he breathed upon his Diſciples, when he bad them to anoint the Sick, and when he curſed the Fig-tree. All men by a naturall inſtinct do ſomwhat like this when they ſecond their Expreſſions with ſome ſigns and motions of their Body, tho they think of no Myſteries. So that you hardly can hear any man being ſomwhat earneſt and ſerious upon any matter, whether of Requeſt, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40360:20"/>Submiſſion, or Excuſes, but you may ſee him at the ſame time either bowing the knee, or joining his hands, or unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering his head, which Acts are, in a manner, civil and natural Sacraments, to confirm his Expreſſion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The truth is, ſuch is the diſpoſition of moſt men, that how ſtrongly ſoever they be perſwaded of the Truth, which they hear, yet will they be far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wrought upon towards their own perſwaſion when they ſee ſome ſigns of this Truth: And tho a true Iſraelire doubts not at all of the preſence of his God, nor a faithfull Diſciple of the promiſe given him that he shall receive the Holy Ghoſt, when Moſes and Chriſt have once paſſed their Word for theſe two Things: yet will their Faith be much ſtrengthned, when one ſees the Ark and the <hi>Cloud,</hi> which were the Sacrament of that, and when the other receives the <hi>Breath,</hi> which was the Sacrament of this. Now the Myſtery of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and of the <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> that followes it, is of that high and important nature, as might juſtly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the Son of God to propoſe them to his Church in the moſt ſutable manner to work in men a deep impreſſion. Therefore as God himſelf in order to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy Moſes more fully that his People should not perish, nor ſo much as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minish
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40360:21"/>under the Thraldom of Egypt; shewed him a <hi>Bush</hi> continuing ſtill whole and entire in the midſt of a great Fire: and in order they might be more firmly perſwaded, that tho they were in a wilderneſs, they were under Gods protection, he made them go all the way under a <hi>Cloud;</hi> that when ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver there should happen any ſtaggering in their <hi>Belief,</hi> both Moſes and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might ſtrengthen it, Moſes by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the <hi>Bush,</hi> and the People by minding the <hi>Cloud;</hi> to the ſame purpoſe hath Chriſt ordained ſome Viſible Signes in his Church, to compleat her <hi>common Faith,</hi> and to aſſure this truth to every one who comes to him, that he shall be cleanſed of his ſins, as certainly as it is certain he ſees ſome <hi>water</hi> which is the ordinary means for <hi>washing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and that he shall be kept up, and fed with a ſupply of all neceſſary Bleſſings, as certainly and really, as it is real and certain he taſts and takes in this <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> which are the ordinary means for preſerving our life and ſtrength.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Beſides, becauſe the Sacraments are deſigned not only to perſwade us more ſtrongly of the truth and Being of the Things, but alſo to acquaint us more familiarly and ſenſibly with their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and nature; theſe Sacraments muſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40360:21"/>have in their <hi>natural conſtitution,</hi> ſome known Qualities that make them fit for this <hi>Sacramental office.</hi> Such hath the <hi>Water</hi> for example, which was ſo deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly choſen for the uſe of holy <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> becauſe of the proper virtue it hath of washing the things that are fowl, of reviving and refreshing them that are dry, and of making fruitful the Barren. Hereupon S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaies plainly, that unleſs the holy Sacraments had ſome ſuch agreement with the <hi>Holy Things,</hi> which they are ſet up to repreſent, they could not be Sacraments at all. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 23. <hi>ad Bonif.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. So the bleſſed Communion is made of two ſuch Elements, as can forthwith expoſe to the ſight and ſenſe of all men, the true ground of its Sacramental and ſignificative Function. This function is twofold; the firſt to repreſent Chriſts <hi>Sufferings:</hi> and the ſecond to repreſent the Bleſſing and the Benefit which we receive from theſe Sufferings. The firſt I ſay to repreſent Chriſts <hi>Sufferings.</hi> This Bread and Wine could neither ſuſtain nor refresh me, had not their intrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Subſtance loſt its firſt condition and eſtate: that is if the one had never fallen under the <hi>Sickle,</hi> the <hi>threshing,</hi> the <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> the <hi>Fire:</hi> and the other under the <hi>Hook,</hi> the <hi>Trampling,</hi> and the <hi>Preſs</hi> of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40360:22"/>bandmen: Nor doth the Son of God ſave me, but by
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>emtying</hi> himſelf in a manner, for a while of his firſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Heaven: and by loſing that ſecond life which he had taken in <hi>Bethlehem.</hi> This Bleſſed Savior is not a Savior by the ſtrength of all the Miracles which He did about <hi>Judea,</hi> nor by any thing that He could ſuffer, as long as He would keep himſelf alive, when he was made faſt to his Croſs. As the beſt Harveſt is not yet <hi>Bread,</hi> as long as it ſtands in the <hi>Field:</hi> nor is the beſt Corn <hi>Bread</hi> likewiſe as long as 'tis kept whole in the <hi>Floor;</hi> both Corn and Harveſt being no more then antecedent Matter for mans Food. Jeſus living in <hi>Galilee,</hi> Jeſus teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about the Temple, Jeſus command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Storms and Waves, when he did walk upon the Sea, if he had proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no further, could not have bin the Bread of life: it muſt be Jeſus <hi>ſuffering,</hi> Jeſus <hi>crucified,</hi> Jeſus <hi>dying:</hi> the grinding Mill, and the burning Fire have of this <hi>Corn</hi> made me this <hi>Bread:</hi> and nothing leſs then Croſs, Wounds, Death, my Lord! my God! could of thy deareſt Son make my Savior?</p>
               <p n="6">6. I ſay ſecondly, this Euchariſtical Bread is inſtituted to repreſent the Fruit and Benefit which we receive both at the Holy Table, and upon all other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40360:22"/>from Chriſts Sufferings, to wit <hi>Maintenance</hi> and <hi>Improvement of life.</hi> As without Bread and Wine, or ſomthing anſwerable to it, the ſtrongeſt Bodies ſoon decay: ſo without the virtue of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, the beſt and holieſt Souls muſt infallibly ſtarve and perish. The Body of the Lord as it was offered up to God in Sacrifice, is the Truth repreſented by the <hi>Paſſover:</hi> and as repreſented to us at the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, is the Truth and Accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment typified by the <hi>Manna.</hi> The one is, as it were the <hi>Seed</hi> and the <hi>Original Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple</hi> whence we are <hi>born:</hi> and the other as the <hi>Bread</hi> wherewith we <hi>live.</hi> That is to ſay, as Bread and Wine do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, but keep up that animal Life, which another Cauſe hath produced: ſo doth our Lord Jeſus by a neceſſary and continual <hi>ſupply</hi> of ſtrength and Grace, repreſented by <hi>Bread and Wine,</hi> ſuſtain, improve, and ſet ſorward that <hi>Spiritual Life</hi> and new Being, which He hath procured us by his Croſs.</p>
               <p n="7">7. For Jeſus the ſecond Adams, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeiz'd, as He hung on the Croſs, with that deep ſleep which God dauſed to fall upon him, gave this new Being to his Church out of that <hi>ſide</hi> which at his Paſſion was opened: and the <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Water,</hi> which then gushed out of his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40360:23"/>Wounds, are the true Principles of life, by reaſon of which his ſpouſe the Church may be called <hi>Eve,</hi> that is true and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Liver. Before she had this new origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal out of her Saviors Paſſion, her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands ſleep, she by her old Extraction was a very Daughter of Death, and a Mother of ſuch Children, as could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to no better Inheritance, then <hi>Curſe</hi> and <hi>Wrath. Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. By the courſe of Nature our Life is but a ſad Progreſs from Birth to Death: and by the courſe of Gods Juſtice a ſadder Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſuch as is that of condemned Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from Priſon to the Place of their Execution. But whilſt we were daily paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on to that moſt dreadful Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Son of God lookt on us, and took our Condemnation upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and under it dyed in our ſteed. Thus by the Death and ſatisfaction of this Victim Juſtice gave way to my Releaſe: God the Father forgave my Sin, and God the Son procured my Life. This Grace is the firſt Purchace of Chriſts Blood, the firſt Irradiation of Gods mercy, and the firſt Breath of ſpiritual Life in our Noſtrils.</p>
               <p n="8">8. But alas! how ſoon would this firſt life vanish away, were it not preſently followed and ſupported by a ſecond? How ſoon would the removal of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40360:23"/>former, be fruſtrated by the commiſſion of other Sins! And ſince I am no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er born in ſin then dead in it, how hard would it be without more help in this corrupted condition to keep dead Lazarus from Rottenneſs! Therefore the Body and Blood of Chriſt once Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed on the Croſs, (to help this firſt) procures a ſecond Life, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, whomſoever it ſaves out of this ſtupid death in ſin: it helps them out of the Puddle, where they did ly like Beaſts without ſenſe of danger, or shame: and it quickens theſe rotten Trees for the producing of better Fruit. The firſt Life being oppoſite to <hi>Condemnation</hi> and Eternal Punishment, belongs properly to the <hi>Blood</hi> that hath ſatisfied divine <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> and ſo removed <hi>Punishment:</hi> and the ſecond which is oppoſite to ſtupid and ſenſeleſs both falling into ſin and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it, relates properly to the <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> that after Propitiation and Pardon washes and ſanctifies the ſinner. Theſe two Lives are the two firſt Effluxes, which proceeded out of Jeſus Chriſt, when his Body was pierced: and both are inſeparable; as the Blood and the water were, which flowed together out of his ſide. Let none, who finds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf clean from the filth and ſpots of his ſin, be afraid of Punishment for them,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40360:24"/>
                  <hi>I have found a Ranſom for him. Job.</hi> 33.24. for the <hi>water</hi> came not without the <hi>Blood.</hi> But let every one that hath a mind to be ſafe from <hi>Punishment</hi> which is taken off by the Blood, ſeek for far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecurity in the purifying of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from all the uncleanneſs of ſin which the <hi>Water</hi> is to wash away: for the <hi>Blood</hi> came not without <hi>water. Chriſt came not by Blood alone, but by water and Blood.</hi> 1 Joh. 5.6.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Over and above theſe two Lives, whereof one conſiſts in <hi>Pardon</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of Punishment; the other in <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification,</hi> and enlivens us from dead works, ſo as not thenceforward to deſerve it as before; there remains beſides a third <hi>Life,</hi> which conſiſts in an abſolute <hi>Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> from Death and other miſeries. This life, as to the ſure Title and Right, is together with the two other purchaſed by the ſame Sacrifice: but as to the real uſe and poſſeſſion, it is reſerved for us in Heaven, and there <hi>hid with Chriſt in God. Coloſſ.</hi> 3.3. Until it be revealed, we appear as if we were dead, theſe two Jewels lying in, and being wrapped about, with the dark Veils of human Mortality, till that Chriſt becoming unto us actual <hi>Redemtion,</hi> as well as actual <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and actual <hi>Sanctification,</hi> this third life ſucceeds to break the Cloud.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:40360:24"/> 10. Now the bleſſed Savior being by his Sacrifice the Author and giver of theſe three Lives, shews himſelf by this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be the preſerver of them alſo: and to this purpoſe ſets up a Table by his Altar, where he engages moſt ſolemnly to feed and nourish our Souls with the conſtant ſupply of his Mercies to the very day of eternal Salvation, as really as he gives and we receive theſe Elements of <hi>Bread and Wine,</hi> which are the uſual meanes of ſuſtaining mortal Bodies until the end of this short Life. <hi>My Father worketh hitherto and I work with him. Ioh.</hi> 95.17. God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſted indeed upon the ſeventh day from the work of <hi>Creating,</hi> and God the Son at the ſame day from the work of <hi>Suffering:</hi> but neither of them will reſt till the day of Redemtion from the work of preſerving, both what the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath produced, and what the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hath ſaved. In the firſt Creation here is a Man and a Woman made of the Flesh, and as it were of the very wounds of her Husband: and there you find a <hi>Tree</hi> planted to maintain both their life and ſtrength. In the Deliverance of Egypt, here is a People ſaved by the Sacrifice of the Paſſeover: and leſt ſo many reſcued out of Egypt, should faint and ſtarve in the Deſert,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40360:25"/>there you ſee an Angel leading them the way with his <hi>Light,</hi> keeping them cool under the Shadow of his <hi>Cloud,</hi> and feeding them through all their journ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with a miraculous ſort of Meat. Jeſus is both in the Original and progreſs of Salvation the Truth foreshewed by theſe Figures. When he dyed upon the Croſs, there he fullfilled that which had bin shadowed forth both by the Sleep and wound of Adam, and by the killing of paſchal Lambs: And when he feeds from Heaven with a continual Effuſion of Bleſſing thoſe ſouls and lives which he hath bin pleaſed to redeem by the effuſion of his own Blood, He is the Truth both of the Tree and of the Angel, which were appointed the one to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Man, and the other to keep Iſrael.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Chriſt relates to theſe four Figures as the <hi>Body</hi> which fulfils them: and the Holy Communion relates to them on the other ſide, as an <hi>Antitype,</hi> that is, as one Image may relate to another, all to expreſs the ſame object. Upon the <hi>breaking</hi> the one and <hi>powring</hi> out the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe conſecrated Elements, you ſee what Chriſt <hi>hath ſuffered,</hi> as upon the wound of Adam, and the <hi>death</hi> of the Paſſeover, Abel, Enoc, and Iſrael might partly ſee, what he should ſuffer: And upon the nourishing nature of this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40360:25"/>Bread, you ſee that which others have ſeen in the <hi>Tree</hi> of life; and in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel raining down Manna, what He would <hi>give.</hi> But this is the advantage of the Holy Communion above all the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Figures. Adam with his open Side, and all Sacrifices with their Blood did foretel only Chriſts Paſſion: and the Tree of life with all its fruit, and the Angel with all his Food did foretel on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his <hi>preſerving</hi> Grace: whereas this Sacrament alone repreſents both his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and <hi>Preſerving,</hi> and beſides theſe, another great Myſtery, by their mutual dependency. What wee take and eat, is made of a Subſtance cut, bruiſed, and put to the fire; that shews my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viors Paſſion; and it was uſed in that manner that it may afford me wholeſom food; that shewes the Benefit which both he gives and I receive out of this dreadful Paſſion. The Angels enjoy ſuch an immortality, and wear ſuch Crowns as coſt God nothing, but the pain he took to give them: ours are more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and coſtly then ſo: Our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in Heaven is not leſs then <hi>Akel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damah,</hi> a Poſſeſſion bought with Chriſts Blood. In this Sacrament here is <hi>Death</hi> repreſented, there <hi>Life;</hi> the Life is mine, the Death my Saviors: and ô bleſſed Jeſus, this my Life comes out of thy Death,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40360:26"/>and the Salvation which I hope for, is purchaſed with all the pain and Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies which Thou didſt ſuffer.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Here Melchiſedek and Aaron wait upon Jeſus Chriſt at this Table, as Moſes and Elias did on the Mount: Theſe two great Prieſts ſtand to ſoreshew, what Chriſt alone is to <hi>perform.</hi> For there is Aaron the Prieſt with Blood, and here Melchiſedek with Bread. There Aaron breaks, sheds and <hi>deſtroies:</hi> here Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedek <hi>feeds</hi> and <hi>bleſſes.</hi> Nay, both are one in Jeſus Chriſt. Firſt Chriſt appears to Sacrifice (upon the Croſs) as Aaron did at his Altar, with Flesh and Blood: and as in Melchiſedeks caſe and figure, with <hi>his own</hi> Flesh, and <hi>his own</hi> Blood. Then as Aaron did uſe to enter once e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very year into the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> Chriſt once for all is aſcended into <hi>Heaven</hi> thence to bleſs us. Act. 3.26. And this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, is the ſtrength, the Food and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshment, which Melchiſedek brought in a figure; that with the help of theſe good Things both Abraham and his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, that is all ſincere Chriſtians, may cheerfully go on their way notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own weakneſs, and all the dangers of their life. Thus here is a double Bleſſing which I wait for; both what Aaron shewed by his <hi>Blood,</hi> and what Melchiſedek shewed by his <hi>Bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:40360:26"/> 13. <hi>Author of my Salvation, and of theſe Myſteries which expreſs it, beſtow on me theſe two Bleſſings, which this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament shews together; Grace for Grace; Mercy, and ſtrength to keep Mercy. Hoſanna O Son of David, ſave and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. Save me that I may not fall under the hand of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer, and preſerve me that after this Salvation I never fall by my own hand. But keep and ſet forward in me notwithſtanding all mine Infirmities the work of thy</hi> faithful Mercies. <hi>Grant that I may not increaſe my Guilt, by my abuſing of what thou gaveſt. My Savior, my Preſerver, give me alwaies what thou giveſt once. Create a new heart within me; but bleſs and keep what Thou createst: and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40360:27"/>increaſe more and more what Thou plantest. O Son of God and Tree of Life, feed with thy ſap this tender</hi> Branch, <hi>which without thee cannot but wither: and ſtrengthen in thee a bruiſed Reed, which without thee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but fall. Father of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Compaſſions, forſake not in the Wilderneſs a feeble Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite, whom thou haſt brought a little way out of Egypt: And let not this poor Soul of mine, which thou hast bleſſed with ſome deſires, and helped a while with ſome tendency to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an Eternal Salvation, ever faint and fall from the right way. The Angel in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs could undoubtedly rain as much Manna, as the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Lambs could shed Blood; Jeſu, the Truth both of thoſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40360:27"/>Lambs and of that Angel, Thou art as able to perfect me with thy Bleſſings out of thy Throne, as thou wert to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem me by thy Sacrifice on thy Croſs. Jeſu Author, Object and Truth of this which by thine appointment I am bidden now to take, perform in me by thy ſufferings what Thou dost exhibit: Eternal</hi> Life, <hi>by this thy</hi> Body broken; <hi>give alſo</hi> Nouriſhment <hi>and maintenance thereby to this ſame Life, for this is the</hi> Bread of Heaven. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:40360:28"/>
               <head>SECTION IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning the Communion, as it is not a Repreſentation only, but a Means of Grace.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. HItherto we have conſidered this holy Sacrament, firſt as a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Memorial</hi> of that Paſſion, wherein Chriſt Jeſus once offered himſelf up to God as <hi>Sacrifice:</hi> and ſecondly as a <hi>ſign</hi> of that nutritive and corroborative Grace (the true Efflux of that Sacrifice) by which ſign he daily offers himſelf to us under the notion of <hi>Meat. For his Flesh is meat indeed, and his Blood is drink in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</hi> Joh. 6.55. And I ingeniouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that the moſt general uſe of the bleſſed Communion runs upon theſe two Notions: and that theſe two main Reſemblances between the <hi>Bread,</hi> and Chriſts <hi>Body,</hi> which qualify the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated Bread (and the conſecrated Wine in the ſame manner) to bear the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Sacrament, do likewiſe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently qualify it, to bear another ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, which it enjoys, of being called the <hi>Lords Body.</hi> However it is moſt certain, that when the Fathers call it ſo, (which Chriſt himſelf taught them to do) they juſtify both His and their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40360:28"/>ſpeech upon the account of <hi>reſemblance,</hi> and of this commerce, (moſt uſual be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Repreſentations,</hi> and objects repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented) of enterchanging their own names. Read the 23. Epiſt. of St. <hi>Auſtin ad Bonif.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. So for example, in the Prophetic <hi>Viſions</hi> and <hi>Dreams,</hi> which moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly were nothing elſe then extempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Sacraments of Things then reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God, thoſe are moſt conſtantly ſaid to be theſe. The 7 Ears of Corn <hi>are</hi> 7 <hi>years,</hi> by the interpretation of Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph. <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.26. The ſeven <hi>Stars</hi> are ſeven <hi>Angels,</hi> in the Revelation of St. John 1.20. The <hi>Sower is the Son of Man,</hi> The <hi>Tares</hi> are <hi>the wicked,</hi> The <hi>Harvest</hi> is the <hi>end of the World,</hi> in the Parables of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.37.38.39. If by chance we meet with Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, that repreſent the Tabernacle, or the Ornaments of Aaron; we uſually ſay, pointing at ſome of theſe Figures, This is the outward Court, this is the Sanctuary, here is the brazen Altar, and there you ſee the Plate of pure Gold, that none was allowed to wear, except the High Prieſt of Iſrael: juſt as walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Palaces and Galleries of great Perſons, we ſay without thinking to ſpeak improperly, that we have ſeen the 12. <hi>Sibyls,</hi> the 12. <hi>Ceſars,</hi> the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40360:29"/>of Epheſus, &amp;c. that is, the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations of all theſe. Now 'tis certain that no Viſions nor Images have ever bin more intended for this end of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting,</hi> then the true Sacraments have bin: therefore it were moſt unreaſonable to think, that theſe ſacred Images should want that Priviledg which all other (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho caſual and profane) are allowed to have, <hi>viz.</hi> to take the name of their Objects. Nay, ſince the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> the <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and the <hi>Baptiſm</hi> have it (for one is called the <hi>Paſsover,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and the other the <hi>Burial</hi> of Chriſt) why should the Holy Communion be without it? Beſides it is not conceivable that Chriſt, who had yet in his hands that Paſchal Bread which was called by the Jews the <hi>Bread of Affliction which their Fathers did eat in Egypt,</hi> becauſe it was the Memorial of it, may not be underſtood after the ſame manner, when a moment after He calls it his Body.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nevertheleſs, altho the literal and immediate ſenſe of theſe Words <hi>This is my Body,</hi> comes to no more; as <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> with many more have in expreſs terms declared it: and as all ancient liturgies muſt needs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, whenſoever they call the Euchariſt, <hi>Type, Image,</hi> or <hi>figure;</hi> for the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40360:29"/>proper and immediate uſe of Images is to repreſent Things. If they chance alſo to have them in themſelves, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey them over to others, it is upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther account, as being <hi>veſſels</hi> or uten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiles, &amp;c. which office is extrinſecal to Sacraments; Nevertheleſs I ſay the end of the bleſſed Communion, the exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and pious deſire of Communicants, and the ſtrength of other Places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture require a great deal more in the Euchariſt then a meer <hi>Memorial</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. 1. <hi>The proper end of the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion;</hi> which is, to make us partakers of Chriſt in another manner and degree, when with faith and repentance wee take and taſt thoſe holy Myſteries, then when with the like diſpoſitions wee do hear the Holy Goſpel. 2. <hi>The Exigency,</hi> and <hi>honeſt deſire of Communicants;</hi> who ſeek no more for a bare Repreſentation or Remembrance of Chriſt crucified, at this Holy Table, then Mary and other devout women did for winding Sheets or Napkins about his Grave. I want and ſeek my Savior himſelf: and I watch for all the opportunities of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Sacrament, for the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that once made S. Peter and S. Iohn run ſo faſt to his Sepulcher; becauſe I hope to find Him there. 3. Laſtly, <hi>the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40360:30"/>full ſenſe and importance of other Places in Scripture,</hi> which allow the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, a much greater Vertue then is that of repreſenting only. <hi>The Cup of Bleſſing which wee bleſs, is it not the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Blood of Chriſt?</hi> 1. Cor. 10.16. For whether the word, which wee render <hi>Communion</hi> be taken in an <hi>active</hi> ſenſe, as 'tis often for <hi>Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> the holy Euchariſt is a Means of communicating the Blood of Chriſt: or tho we take it but in a <hi>neuter</hi> and <hi>intran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive</hi> ſenſe; yet the holy Euchariſt will be ſtill a Myſtery, wherein one way or other true Chriſtians shall find, not a Commemoration or Repreſentation on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but a Communion alſo with the Blood ſo repreſented and remembred.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The reall Efficacy which the Holy Communion hath to convey Grace and Bleſſing on the true Chriſtian Receiver, is evidently demonſtrated by the oppoſite Efficacy it hath to convey a Curſe and Deſtruction on the Profane. <hi>Whoſoever</hi> ſayes S. Paul, <hi>eats of this Bread unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, eats damnation to himſelf.</hi> Now certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this would be as much to think <hi>unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily</hi> as to eat <hi>unworthily</hi> of this holy Bread, to think it might be really pernicious when it is abuſed, but not really bliſsful and ſaving in its right uſe; and that this Bread, which we eat of, should be an
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40360:30"/>
                  <hi>effectual</hi> Communion to procure death, but meerly <hi>Sacramental</hi> only to shew, and not to procure Salvation. S. Paul ſets out the Character of the unworthy Communicant, by <hi>not diſcerning the Lords Body:</hi> and thereby declares him <hi>guilty of the very Body and Blood of Chriſt.</hi> That is to ſay, that whoſoever offers to abuſe this Sacrament, plunges himſelf into their Crime, who have abuſed Chriſt himſelf: and that that Villain goes hand in hand with Judas, with Pilate, with both Jews and Romans who murthered Him. What therefore can be thought of thoſe good Souls, who approach to this Sacrament with faith, humility, and a trembling Reverence, but that they will return home as much Juſtified and full of grace after their Devout, as the other shall full loaded with Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, after their impious uſage: and that God will be as merciful in reckoning thoſe among the Righteous <hi>Mary, Joſeph, Nicodemus,</hi> as He is Juſt againſt theſe, when upon this account he shuts up their Souls with the Sinners, that in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deed crucified him. And God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that the Body of Chriſt, who came to ſave, not deſtroy, should not diffuſe as much of its <hi>Savor of life</hi> for the life and Salvation of Devout Souls, as it doth, of its <hi>Savor of Death</hi> for the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40360:31"/>Death of the Impious. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The manner of this real Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication and Conveyance, is the great unfathomable Myſtery, which the Holy Fathers have ever admired: and which therefore we neither need, nor do take upon us to explain. The Shepherds think themſelves happy with the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage brought to them by an Angel, <hi>This day is born to you a Savior,</hi> Luke 2.11. tho they know nothing of the way of his moſt miraculous Birth: and the honeſt Iſraelites ought not to receive Manna leſs thankfully (as they do not leſs effectually) tho they know neither of what matter, nor by what means the Heavens, the Air, or the Clouds can thus every morning shed about their Tents this ſtrange Meat. I muſt not wonder if the waies of the Lord be unknown to me in his Miracles, ſince they are ſo very often in his moſt ordinary works. And if David, tho a Prophet, cannot think upon that natural virtue, which makes Bones and Veins every day out of that feed, that is apparently nothing like to all theſe parts of Mans body, but he cries out <hi>I have bin ſtrangely and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully made!</hi> Pſ. 139.13. Who am I to pretend to a clear underſtanding of that hidden and incomprehenſible wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, wherewith God is pleaſed to make
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40360:31"/>out of <hi>Water,</hi> or <hi>Wine,</hi> or <hi>Bread</hi> (in themſelves weak Elements) ſtrong and ſupernatural Organs for Mens Souls and ſalvation?</p>
               <p n="7">7. It is true indeed, that Bread, Wine, and Water can without much ado come up ſo high as to become a Sacrament to <hi>ſignify:</hi> ſince the Act of <hi>ſignifying</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends meerly on <hi>Inſtitution.</hi> Yet this Inſtitution, ſuch as may make a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, muſt needs proceed both from a Divine and an almighty Origine. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> I ſay; to give a Sacred Character: and <hi>Almighty</hi> withal; to juſtify and maintain it. For example, after the Flood no man or Angel had authority to make of the Rainbow a Myſtery, that should ſignify the worlds preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from Drowning: and if either Men or Angels had taken on them that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; none of them had the power to make it true; that is, to make it a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing infallible Evidence that the world shall never perish by water. So in the Church neither Apoſtles nor Bishops have any more Right to confer either upon the <hi>water</hi> of Baptiſm, or upon the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> of the Holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, a Sacramental or repreſentative Office, then they have power to make good their Repreſentation by conferring the Bleſſings promiſed by it. And it is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40360:32"/>ſpecially to this purpoſe, that moſt of the Expreſſions and Epiphonemas of the holy Doctors are to be underſtood, when they ſtand ſomtimes amazed at the infinit Power of God, either in the Inſtitution, or the uſe of theſe Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: God alone being able to raiſe, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or Blood or any Thing elſe to the Order of <hi>Sacraments.</hi> But to raiſe them a ſtep higher, that is to the Dignity of ſtanding for true <hi>Means</hi> and <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> which may convey on us thoſe Graces, which by their proper inſtitution they repreſent; there is the Finger of God indeed, and there is a fitter matter for Mens admiration, then Mens knowledg.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Here then I come to Gods Altar with a full perſwaſion that theſe words <hi>This is my Body,</hi> promiſe me more then a figure: that this holy Banquet is not a Repreſentation made of outward shews without ſubſtance: and that it is not ſo dangerous a Myſtery but that the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious uſe of it may convey to me (at the leaſt) as many, and as great Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, as the profane abuſe of it may throw on the Abuſer Plagues and Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. But how theſe Myſteries become in my behalf the ſupernatural Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſuch Bleſſings; it is enough for me to admire. One thing I know (as ſaid the blind man after he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40360:32"/>his ſight. S. <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.25.) <hi>he laid Clay upon mine Eyes, and behold I ſee.</hi> He hath bleſſed and given me this Bread, and my Soul received Comfort. I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believe that Clay hath nothing in it ſelf, that could have wrought ſuch a Miracle, as Iſrael never ſaw the like: And I know as much of this Bread, that it is not ſuch a Jewel as may contain in its ſubſtance, or impart from it ſelf to others, Grace, Holineſs, and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is the juice and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Chriſts Body. Only I am perfectly ſatisfied, that 'tis the conſtant way of God, to produce his greateſt Works, at the preſence (tho not by the virtue) of the moſt uſeleſs Inſtruments. At the very ſtroke of a Rod, He part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed once in two the red Sea. At the blowing ſome Trumpets, He tumbled down maſſy ſtrong walls. At ſome few washings in Jordan, he cured Naaman of a Plague, which naturally was incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: and as ſoon as but a shadow did paſs by, or ſome Oyl was dropped down, or ſome Cloaths were toucht, preſently virtue went out, not of Rods, or Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, or shade, or Clothes, but of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>Virtue,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is gon out of me:</hi> and thus he cured the ſick, &amp;c. Since then he hath inſtituted and adopted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelf the Sacraments of the Goſpel,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40360:33"/>as the Repreſentative of his Sacred Body and Blood: why may he not take the ſame courſe for the diſpenſing of his Mercies, at the uſe of his Ordinances? and why should not his very body pour out Effuſions of life as well when we take in his Sacraments, as when others did touch his Clothes, which ſurely had leſs Priviledg?</p>
               <p n="9">9. Under the Law, the Right hand of the Lord had the preeminence, the Right hand of the Lord brought theſe mighty Things to paſs, either when the red Sea opened a way for Iſrael, or when the Rock of Horeb powred Rivers to refresh them. Now under the Goſpel, It is Chriſt himſelf with his Body and Blood once offered to God upon the Croſs, and ever ſince ſtanding before him in Heaven as the <hi>Lamb ſlain.</hi> Rev. 5.6. who fills his Church continually with the Propitiations and Perfumes of his Sacrifice, when after the receiving of the holy Sacrament, faithful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants return home richer then they came, with the firſt fruits of Salvation. For Baptiſmal <hi>Water,</hi> and Conſecrated <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> can contribute no more to it, then the Rod of Moſes, or the Oyl of the Apoſtles did, which was no more then their <hi>Motion</hi> and their <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</hi> But yet ſince theſe ſimple Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40360:33"/>and inconſiderable Preſences are ſo cloſely attended by Chriſts inſtitution and working, that he is pleaſed to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to them the Bleſſing wrought out by himſelf, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. O my God whenſoever thou wilt bid me, <hi>go and wash in Jordan,</hi> or be <hi>baptiſed and wash away my ſins,</hi> I will doubt no more to be made clean either of my Leproſy, or of my Sins, then if I had bin bathed in thy Blood: And whenſoever thou wilt be pleaſed to ſay unto me, go, take and eat this Bread, which I have bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and which now I have given thee, I will doubt no more of being fed with the true Bread of Life, then if I were eating thy very Flesh.</p>
               <p n="10">10. In this manner faithful Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants eat as effectually of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt by receiving its ſtrength and virtue, as the Saints eat of the Tree of life. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.2. becauſe they eat the Fruit of that Tree: or Iſrael did drink of the Rock, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. becauſe they did drink of the Stream that flowed from it. Once my Savior could ſay, that ſome Body had touched him, tho they had touched but his Clothes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Woman had reached both her Faith and her Hand ſo near as to be healed by the Divine warmth and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue that proceeded then out of him, as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40360:34"/>if she had touched his very Flesh. The truth is, we really touch, have or enjoy the Thing it ſelf, when we are within that diſtance, where we may enjoy its virtue. So the Church was <hi>clothed with the ſun.</hi> Rev. 12.1. becauſe shee had all about Her its Brightneſs: and by the Holy Baptiſm we are ſaid to <hi>put on Chriſt.</hi> Galat. 3.27. becauſe we then receive the Robes of his Righteouſneſs, and that which was typified by that Garment which God made of skins (which implies the death of Victims) to cover Adams Nakedneſs.</p>
               <p n="11">11. This Victim having bin offered up both in the fulneſs of times, and in the midſt of the habitable World, which properly is Chriſts great Temple, and thence being carried up to Heaven, which is his proper Sanctuary, thence he ſpreads all about us Salvation, as the Burnt offering did its ſmoke: as the Golden Altar did its Perfumes: and as the burning Candleſtic its Lights. And thus Chriſts Body and Blood have every where, but eſpecially at the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion a moſt true and <hi>real Preſence.</hi> When he offered himſelf upon Earth, the Vapor of his Attonement went up, and darkned the very Sun: and by rent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great Vail, it cleerly shewed he had made a way into Heaven. Now
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40360:34"/>ſince He is gon up to Heaven, thence he ſends down on Earth the Graces that ſpring continually both from his ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Sacrifice, and from the continual. Interceſſions which attend it. So that it is in vain to ſay, <hi>who will go up into Heaven?</hi> ſince without either aſcending or deſcending, this Sacred Body of Jeſus fills with Attonement and Bleſſing the remoteſt Parts of this Temple.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Of theſe Bleſſings, Chriſt from above is pleaſed to diſpenſe ſomtimes more, ſomtimes leſs, into theſe <hi>Inferior Courts of the People,</hi> either according to the ſeveral degrees of their Faith, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſeveral waies and times, which He hath appointed to them, for preſenting themſelves nearer to Him. All worshippers do not come to him with the ſame Faith: nor have all ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and waies, (tho approved and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Him) the ſame or equal Priviledg: And his Ordinances in the Church, as well as his Stars in Heaven, differ in Glory one from another. <hi>Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Prayer, Hearing</hi> of the Word, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic and private <hi>Services,</hi> and all like ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Duties, are all very good Veſſels to draw water from this Well of Salvation: but yet they are not all equal. The bleſſed Communion muſt exceed as much in Bleſſings, when well uſed, as it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40360:35"/>in danger of a Curſe, when it is not. <hi>In all places,</hi> ſaies God, where I <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord my Name, there I will come to thee, and bleſs thee. Exod.</hi> 20.24. But in thoſe Places and Ordinances, which He hath in an eſpecial manner ſet out to record his <hi>Paſſion,</hi> and to renew the Sacrifice of his Body; he will certainly come with ſuch a fulneſs of Bleſſings, as at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this Sacred Body, which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Seat of Bleſſings: the Bread which we do break, being the Communion of his Body: juſt as the eating of the <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leavened Loaves</hi> were (out of Jeruſalem) the communion to the <hi>Paſsover,</hi> which was the type of Chriſt Crucified. <hi>Chriſt our Paſsover,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle, <hi>is Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed for us: therefore let us keep the Feaſt,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 5.7.8.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Our life in general is the time of this Feſtival: and the Bleſſed Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, is the Bread and Wine of the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet. Therefore as they of Iſrael, who for ſome lawful impediment could not eat the Lamb in Jeruſalem, nor durſt, becauſe of the Law, ſacrifice and eat it at home, had nevertheleſs the Benefit both of the Paſsover and other Holy Things of the Temple, by virtue of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>var Feaſtings, which they were allowed to keep with unleavened Bread and bitter Herbs in the Country. Our Euchariſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40360:35"/>eating ſupplies now this very Office: and derives on worthy Communicants, as far as their Salvation is concerned, the virtue of Chriſts Sacrifice, in as large and ſaving a manner, as if they were preſent at His Altar, and at the hour of His Paſſion. <hi>The Lord bleſs thee out of his holy Seat.</hi> For then it was the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Lord towards his firſt Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (as certainly He hath no leſs mercy for the ſecond) <hi>virtually</hi> to diffuſe the Propitiation and ſtrength of Holy Things from his Palace, into their Tents; and to bleſs them both <hi>inherently</hi> with all the Graces, and <hi>imputatively</hi> with all the Right, which could be conferred on them whoſe fault 'tis not, if they cannot either eat the Paſsover nearer the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or wait upon Chriſt at his Croſs.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Thus this great and Holy Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry extends and communicates the Death of the Lord, both as <hi>offering himſelf to God,</hi> and as <hi>giving himſelf to Men.</hi> As he offered himſelf to God; it enters me both into that myſterial Body, which is reputed as dead with Chriſt, and into their Society, priviledg and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, for whom He was pleaſed to dye: it ſets me among the precious ſtones of Aarons Ephod, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28. cloſe to the Breaſt, and on the very shoulders of that Eternal Prieſt, whilſt he offers up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40360:36"/>and intercedes for his ſpiritual Iſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el: and by this means it conveyes to me the <hi>Communion of his Sufferings. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip.</hi> 3.10. whence will infallibly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed another Communion in all his Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Glories. Under the ſecond no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as <hi>He offers himſelf to Men;</hi> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Euchariſt is, after the Sacrifice for ſin, the true Feſtival and Sacrifice of Peace offerings, and the <hi>Table</hi> purpoſely ſet up to receive thoſe Mercies, that are ſent down from the <hi>Altar. Take, and eat, this is my Body which was broken for you. And this is the Blood that was shed for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. Here then I wait at the Lords Table, that both <hi>shews</hi> me what an Apoſtle, who had Heaven for his School, had the greateſt mind to ſee and learn, and offers me the richeſt Gift, that a Saint can receive on Earth, the <hi>Lord Jeſus crucified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amen Jeſu, my Lord and my God, give me all this which Thou showeſt; and grant with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al that I may both devoutly take, and faithfully keep, what Thou art pleaſed to give. Bleſs
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40360:36"/>this thine own Ordinance, and make it of a</hi> true Sign, <hi>an</hi> effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Means <hi>of thy Grace: then bleſs and ſanctify my Heart alſo, and make it a fit Temple for thy Mercies. Certainly Thou wilt deal with me in theſe thy Myſteries, O God of Truth, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy</hi> faithfulneſs; <hi>but diſpoſe alſo my heart ſo towards the right uſing of them, that I may ſafely wish it may be don according to my</hi> Faith. <hi>O Father which art in Heaven, here. I offer up to thee my Soul, and thou offereſt to me thy Son. The Oblation which I make is alas an unclean habitation to receive the</hi> Holy One <hi>of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el: and a Tent infected with Leproſy, therein to Lodg the</hi> Saint <hi>of the Lord. Come in nevertheleſs, come in high and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40360:37"/>Prieſt, but wash thy houſe at thy coming. Let no ill ſavor of the grave, no more then that of Lazarus, keep thee ſo far from the Sepulcher, and from the vile condition wherein I ly, but that thy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with thy Voice, and thy Blood with thy Sacrament, may reach to me to raiſe me up: And let none of thoſe uncleanneſses, that after the Law of Moſes, did defile them who came too near, keep off the great Saint of the Lord from touching, and heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me. Evil Spirits enter ſomtimes into ſwept houſes, to make them foul.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>But O Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and hallowing Spirit of God draw nigh unto my Soul, which of it ſelf is foul already, to make it clean. I am a poor
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40360:37"/>ſinful, and unleſs thou help, a loſt perſon, but yet ſuch as I am ſinful and loſt, I wait for thy Salvation. Come in, O Lord, with thy Salvation to a dying Man, to make him whole; to a ſinner tyed hand and foot with the bonds of iniquity, to releaſe him: to one who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes his ſins, to abſolve him. Finally come in my Savior, as thou didſt to the Publican, both to make me better and to ſave me. O let this day Salvation come to this Houſe. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:40360:38"/>
               <head>SECTION V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Bleſſed Communion as being a Pledg of the Happineſs and Glory to come.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THe bleſſed Communion opens ſuch a treaſure of Bleſſings on the two ſides which look towards the paſt or preſent Time, (as I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered it) as it may very well take up both all the eyes of Cherubins in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Myſteries, and all the hands of the numerous Iſraelites in gathering up all the Manna, that it contains: yet it hath one other ſide or proſpect more, which goes beyond the two former, as much as the future Bleſſings exceed the preſent, and as the Glory, which we hope for, exceeds the ſmall degree of grace, which we poſſeſs. The bleſſed Communion which is a ſpeciall Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ordained of Chriſt both to preſent a new (as to our uſe) his <hi>Paſſion,</hi> and to convey on us the <hi>preſent Graces,</hi> which flow out of this Paſſion, doth there with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all aſſure us likewiſe of all the <hi>Happineſs to come;</hi> whereof the received Graces are a hopeful <hi>Earneſt,</hi> and this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under this third notion, is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Pledg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Now, tho what is given before
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40360:38"/>hand for <hi>Earneſt,</hi> and what is engaged by way of <hi>Pledg,</hi> come all to one, in point of Validity and obligingneſs: yet they quite differ many times both in their uſe and in their intrinſecal value. Whence it comes to paſs, that <hi>Earneſts</hi> may be allowed upon <hi>account</hi> for part of the <hi>Payment</hi> which is promiſed; whereas <hi>Pledges</hi> are recalled, and taken back; as the <hi>Seal</hi> and <hi>Staff</hi> of Juda once were. <hi>Gen.</hi> 38. Thus for example, zeal, Charity, and theſe degrees of Holineſs, which God beſtowes at the uſe of holy Sacraments, will remain ſtill ours in Heaven, and there make part of our Happineſs; whereas the Sacraments them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves shall be kept back, and shall not appear more in Heaven then did the Cloudy Pillar in Canaan, or do now the shadows of the Law under the time of the Goſpel. Certainly we shall have no need, either of theſe ſacred Images of Chriſt; when we shall ſee him face to face, or of theſe Pledges to aſſure us of that Glory, which is to be revealed, when we shall actually poſſeſs it. But till that day, the holy Communion hath this third uſe, namely of being a Pledg and an aſſurance from the Lord, that in his good time he will crown us with Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Happineſs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Our bleſſed Savior pointed at it,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40360:39"/>when He ſaid to his Diſciple, the Holy Cup being in his hand, that he would drink no more of that Fruit, till he should drink it new in the Kingdom of his Father. Luk. 22.18. In the reall purpoſe of God, his Church and Heaven go both together: That being the way that leads to this, as the Holy Place, to the Holyeſt: and both <hi>Holy Place,</hi> and <hi>Holyeſt</hi> come to this one Thing, which Chriſt calls the <hi>Kingdom of God.</hi> Let them not, whom He hath invited to eat and drink at Abrahams <hi>Table,</hi> trouble themſelves about the Room where our bleſſed Savior will feed them; for tho it were but in this inferior part of the kingdom, where this Patriarck was <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> it it a ſufficient aſſurance, that in time He will alſo make them ſit in that other Palace, where this holy Man is now <hi>happy:</hi> and whoſoever are admitted to the <hi>Dinner</hi> of the Lamb ſlain, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.4. unleſs they be wanting to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, muſt not doubt of being admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to that wedding <hi>Supper</hi> of the ſame Lamb, who once was dead, but now is <hi>Living for ever.</hi> Luk. 14.16. <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.9.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The conſequence and connexion that theſe two Feſtivals have one with the other, was moſt ſweetly alluded to by our Savior, when he asked the Diſciples,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40360:39"/>who talked of ſitting at his Right hand in his Glory, whether they could paſs to it throught the ſame <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the ſame <hi>Cup. Mark.</hi> 10.37.38. And S. Paul meant as much, when he ſaid that by the holy Euchariſt we ſet forth the Lords death <hi>til he come.</hi> 1. Cor. 11.26. Both referring and continuing this holy Myſtery to the ſecond <hi>Coming</hi> of Chriſt, not only as to the End, where it muſt ceaſe: but chiefly as to the Scope, that it looks to; and to that happineſs at his coming, where it muſt be full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. And truly, ſince our Savior ſcarce ever ſpeaks of his own death, but as a forerunner and Preparative to his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: and often joines in one Clauſe, and delivers as it were with one breath, both his Crucifiction and his Glory, Mark. 10.34. it it very fit, unleſs we put aſunder theſe two Things, which Chriſt commonly did put together, that the Sacrament which he inſtituted pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely to repreſent the one, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready accomplished, should at the leaſt caſt an Eye towards the other, which we look for.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Nay, it muſt look and lead that way upon another and much ſtronger neceſſity. Our Savior hath given us three kinds of life by his Paſſion, and He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to nourish and maintain us in every
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40360:40"/>one of them, by theſe tokens of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> which he hath made his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. This Sacrament affords help and improvement for two as tis ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but there is a third more, that we are not yet come to: This is that eternal Life, for which this preſent world is too vile an Element, and we our ſelves as yet too vile veſſells. Till we acquire by Grace and pious Endeavors a greater Perfection; and till we grow to that ſtature as may fit us to bear up that weight of Eternal Glory: we are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of age to enjoy our Inheritance, nor of ability to manage well that great Eſtate, and wear thoſe noble Ornaments that attend it: and therefore it lyes hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from us with Chriſt in God, and as it were under his Cuſtody. <hi>I Know whom I have believed, and I am perſwaded he is able to keep that which I have committed unto him againſt that Day.</hi> 2. Tim. 1.12. that is; by Faith we depoſit this great Treaſure in the hands of God to keep: and God by this Sacrament aſſures us and engages himſelf, that he will both keep it ſafe for us, and reſtore it to us whenſoever we are fit for it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This third uſe is the Crown and the Accomplishment of the two other: And tho the Sacrament hath three Faces, and looks three ſeveral waies, the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40360:40"/>Paſt, the preſent, and the future; yet as to the main end, theſe three aim at one and the <hi>ſame Glory.</hi> The firſt uſe of this Sacrament is to ſet out as new and fresh the great and holy Sufferings, which have purchaſed our Title to Everlaſting Happineſs: the ſecond is both to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the quality, and to afford us the help of all neceſſary Graces (true Effluxes of theſe Sufferings) to capacitate us towards it: and the third is to aſſure us that when we are capacitated by theſe Graces; God, and his Chriſt will faithfully ſurrender to us the Purchace it ſelf, that is, eternal Happineſs. And theſe three Parts put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether make up the proper and true ſenſe of theſe words, <hi>Take and eat this is my Body:</hi> for the conſecrated Bread is not ſaid to be the Lords Body only, becauſe it repreſents the Lords Body, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe alſo as to our preſent uſe on Earth, it doth as good as exhibit it: and as to our Happineſs in Heaven bought with the price of this Body, it is the moſt ſolemn Inſtrument to aſſure our Title to it.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Thus the conſecrated Elements are no more the Body and Blood of Chriſt, in that ſenſe that Pictures and Maps ſet about Rooms, are commonly called <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Countries</hi> only becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent them: but as Patents alſo grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40360:41"/>by Kings, or other Deeds and Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences left in our houſes by our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, are called Lands, Eſtates, and Manors, becauſe they convey over to us moſt really both the Title and Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of all the goods which they men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Repreſent to your mind Jacob di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding among his Children every Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of his Eſtate, and withal ſurrendring the Titles that belong to each Diviſion; take thou this, Joſeph, this is the <hi>Field,</hi> which my Grand Father Abraham bought of Hephron, and you Manaſehs, come you hither, this is the <hi>Land,</hi> which I got from the Amorite. It is moſt certain that the ſurrendring ſuch Inſtruments, (altho in themſelves but Papers, or Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) is in very deed nothing leſs then giving away the very Lands: And Deeds and lands may very well go together under one Name, ſince by giving whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Deeds or Lands, whether Patents, or Priviledges, Fathers and other Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors do both intend and effect the ſame Thing. If it happen ſomtimes among men that Right and Poſſeſſion take not one way: that our beſt Titles are laid aſide: and that we cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy thoſe Eſtates, whereof either our Kings, or Fathers have left us moſt clear Evidences; this falls out ſo by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Rencounters of either weakneſs,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40360:41"/>or injuſtice, or ignorance, which are not to be found in Chriſt. Here then Chriſt our bleſſed Savior being deſirous before his death, as by a Deed of his laſt will, to ſettle upon his true Diſciples both ſuch a meaſure of his Grace in this life, as might in part make them Holy, and after this life ſuch a fullneſs of all Bleſſings, as might make them eternally happy; He delivers into their hands, by way of Inſtrument and Conveyance, the bleſſed Sacrament of his Body and Blood (the true Root and ſtem of all Bleſſings) in the ſame manner, as to his Intention, but in a ſurer way, as to the Event and effect, as Kings uſe to beſtow Dignities by the beſtowing of a <hi>ſtaff,</hi> or <hi>ſword,</hi> and Fathers paſs as much as they pleaſe of their Eſtates on their Children, by giving them ſome few <hi>writings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. The true reaſon of all this, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Giver is not able to transfer into his Friends hands Houſes and Lands, becauſe they are of an immoveable Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and therefore this muſt be ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſubſtituting in ſtead of Lands, ſome Ceremonies, forms, or tokens, which may viſibly paſs from hand to hand: and shew to all ends and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes both the Intention, that the one hath to paſs away, and the power, which the other hath to take and enjoy
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40360:42"/>what is given him. Now Chriſt and his Eſtate, his Happineſs and his Glory, his Eternity and his Heaven, are not Things that may be moved more eaſily, then the Mountains or the Earth: and therefore not to be diſpoſed of in any other real manner, then great immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veable Eſtates are. Therefore the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Iſrael was once conferred upon David, with ſome drops of that Sacred Oil, which Samuel poured on his head. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.13. The Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt is in <hi>full value,</hi> and Heaven with all its fulneſs is in <hi>ſure Title</hi> inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on true Chriſtians by thoſe ſmall por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which they receive at the Bleſſed Communion: the Miniſter of Chriſt having, as to this effect, as much power from his Maſter, for what he acts, as any Prophet or any Angel ever had, for what they did.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Hence it appears, what crime it is <hi>not to diſcern the Lords Body.</hi> It is to do worſe then Eſau did, who ſold his Birthright for a trifle: it is to value at the ſame rate the Anointing of a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> and the compoſition of a <hi>Perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer:</hi> it is to take the Lords Body for a deſpicable Morſel of Bread. In a word, 'tis to perform the action of a Beaſt, that devours but the groſs and earthy Matter of this Sacrament: and have
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:40360:42"/>nothing of a Chriſtian or rational crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who elevates his Soul to that Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which by Chriſts inſtitution it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents, and to the Price of that Body, which it promiſes. For ſince the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per eſſence of Sacred ſigns or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments conſiſts not in what they <hi>are</hi> in their nature, but in what they <hi>ſignify</hi> by divine inſtitution; hence it happens infallibly, that when the Sacraments are abuſed, the injury muſt needs light, not upon them in their own natural Being, <hi>Bread, Wine,</hi> and <hi>Water,</hi> which upon this account are not at all conſiderable; but upon the Holy myſteries, the Body and Blood of Chriſt himſelf, who is the main object of their formal Being, that is, their Signification. And therefore the Apoſtle ſpeaks moſt exactly, when he ſaies, that whoſoever eats of this <hi>Bread unworthily,</hi> doth not <hi>diſcern,</hi> or doth not ſanctify, but uſes as a common and profane thing, the very Body of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="11">11. In this profane want of Diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 'tis hard to ſay whether the Sin, or the Punishment be the greater. For the ſin is abominable, ſince not the Bread, but Chriſt himſelf ſuffers the wrong: the <hi>Bread</hi> being not here concerned at all, nor more abuſed by the Villain that abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> then is the Earth, the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40360:43"/>water or any other common matter of human Bodies, by the Murtherer, that kills a <hi>Man:</hi> or then are Braſs and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by the Rebels, who pull down their Princes <hi>Statues:</hi> or then Parchment, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and Ink, by that unnatural Son, who tears and tramples upon the Deeds, and the laſt will of his Father. Only there is this difference, that in theſe laſt Inſtances, the Outrage proceeds but from the Earth, the Braſs, the Marble, the Paper, and other ſuch common Matter, to the Man, King, or Fathers perſons, who should have bin conſidered, and who alone ſuffer the wrong: whereas in abuſing the bleſſed Sacraments the ſin flys a great deal higher, namely to the very Face of Jeſus Chriſt, for whoſe Body and Blood they ſtand. So that as the Holy Communion is not expoſed in the Church under the notion of Bread and Wine: the faithful Communicants do appear there to receive Chriſt, and the faithleſs to abuſe Him.</p>
               <p n="11">11. But if this Attemt is impious, the Punishment that attends it, is moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. It is a very ſad miſchance when Dogs or Apes tear like loſe paper all to fitters the Titles and aſſurances of a good Eſtate: and who would not pitty that wretch, who in his mad Paſſion had thrown into the ſea, the very Keyes,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40360:43"/>which were given him, to Juſtify the Propriety of vaſt Treaſures, in ſuch Houſes, as theſe keyes might open. Blind Villains, you cannot diſcern, either among theſe Papers, the Original <hi>Deeds</hi> of your Eſtate: or among all theſe Inſtruments the <hi>keyes,</hi> that might both aſſure and give you admittance to immenſe Riches. Whenſoever you eat of this Bread, and drink of this Cup thus unworthily; <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy</hi> men, you do not diſcern the Pledges of your <hi>Salvation:</hi> nay moſt <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious</hi> as you are, you neither diſcern nor will honor the Body and Blood of your <hi>Savior,</hi> which would bring ſalvation to you. At once both impious and unhappy men, you deſpiſe and caſt away from you, both the <hi>Salvation</hi> and the <hi>Savior!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Lord Jeſu! who hast ordained this Mystery for a</hi> Communion <hi>of thy Body: for a</hi> Means <hi>of advancement and proficiency in Holineſs: and for an infallible</hi> Pledg <hi>of Eternal Salvation, which thou hast pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by thy Body, and which thou preparest thy People to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40360:44"/>receive by this Proficiency in Holineſs; now Lord in mercy look on me, help my unbelief, increaſe my Faith, and order the Soul of thy Servant, who is to take theſe Holy Things. Then ſince thou thy ſelf</hi> origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally <hi>giveſt them, (tho not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly, but by the miniſtry of thy Diſciples,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1, 2.</note>) <hi>In giving them bleſs them alſo: and bleſs them whilſt I receive them: that they may be efficacious to ſettle me in the Communion of thy Sufferings which they exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit and</hi> ſhew forth: <hi>to feed me with that living Bread, which they</hi> preſent: <hi>and to ſanctify me for that eternal Happineſs, which they</hi> promiſe. <hi>O Lord thou knoweſt my ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleneſs, my Growning is not hid
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40360:44"/>from thee look on a poor Sinner at thy Table, as thou didſt on him who hung by thy Croſs. O Lord my God, remember me now, when thou art come into thy Kingdom.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 23.42.</note> 
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Eternal Prieſt, who art gon up on high, there to receive Gifts for men; fill my Heart I beſeech thee with bleſſings out of thy holy Seat, as now thou fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt my Mouth with the Holy Things of thy Church: and ſo diſpoſe me by thy Grace to eat both ſpiritually and really the Fleſh of that Sacrifice, which thou didſt offer without the Gate, and which this Sacrament ſets before me here in thy Courts, that thence I may be admitted into that Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40360:45"/>Sanctuary, which thy Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice hath opened, and which this Sacrament invites me to. This is the Bread which the Lord hath prepared for his Children, and which he ſends me now by the hand of one of his Angels. O that in the ſtrength of this Meat, I may walk as Elijah did, my fourty daies, or as Iſrael, my fourty years, and come at laſt to that Holy Mountain, where without the help of any Bread, or the Miniſtry of any Angels, I ſhall ſee my God face to face. Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and bleſsed, and bleſſing Spirit of God, bleſs me now, and help me to drink ſo worthily of this fruit of the Vine, that I may drink it new in the Kingdom of my Father. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:40360:45"/>
               <head>SECTION VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Holy Euchariſt, as it implies a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. And firſt of the Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorative Sacrifice.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. IT is a certain truth that there never was on Earth a true Religion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome kind of Sacrifices: and 'tis a very great lye to ſay that now the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian should want them. The Jews and the Pagans, who firſt aſperſed the Church of Chriſt with this ſlander, did it upon ſuch a reaſon, as became them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſaw neither Altars ſet up, nor Beaſts ſlain and burnt among them. Thus the Pagans accuſed the Jews of adoring nothing but Clouds, becauſe they had no Gods of Stone, or Silver in their Synagogues: and thus ſilly men may think now, that the world is deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Angels, becauſe they do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo often as they did in ancient times, in the shape and forms of Men. The truth, is as what appeared like a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, was not an Angel: nor what was Stone, or Silver could be a God: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſlaughter of poor beaſts could ever be true Sacrifices. <hi>Thou delighteſt not in Oblations, the Sacrifice of God is a broken Spirit.</hi> Many among the Jews much leſs quick ſighted then the Prophets were,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40360:46"/>confeſſed as much: nor certainly could any reaſon permit them to imagine, that Flesh and Blood, which in all their Scriptures paſſes both for the weakeſt and the vileſt of Things, could be the beſt and the ſoundeſt part of Sacrifices.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of all the Carnal Sacrifices, which the Jews do reduce to ſix kinds (beſides many more Oblations) none ever had any ſaving reality, as to the washing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of ſins but in dependance on Jeſus Chriſt our Lord: and as to our ſervice and duty towards God, which they were alſo to repreſent, none had this ſecond end ſo fully performed under the Law, as it muſt be under the Goſpel. The bleſſed Communion alone, when whole, and not mutilated, concenters and brings together theſe two great Ends (full Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piation of ſins, and acceptable Duty to God) towards which all the old Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices never look't, but as either ſimple Engagements, or weak shadows. As for the firſt, which is Expiation of ſins; 'tis moſt certain that the Sacrifice of Jeſus Chriſt alone hath bin ſufficient for it: and that if all both men and Angels were joined to it, it were not to add too, but to receive from its fulneſs. It is moſt certain alſo, that this great Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice being both of an infinit virtue to ſatisfy the moſt ſevere Juſtice, and of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40360:46"/>an infinite virtue to produce at once all the Effects, that can be expected of it; it were impiety to think, it should need to be don again, as weak and infirm Cauſes muſt, in order to make up by degrees and at ſeveral times their full Effect. This was perhaps the want of Faith, which the holy Scripture taxes in Moſes. <hi>Num.</hi> 20.12. (which it is hard to find in any thing els) to ſtrike a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time, and without order, that myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Rock, which to ſtrike once had bin enough: for this ſecond blow could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed but of a faithleſs miſtruſt that the firſt, which alone was commanded, could not ſuffice. But it were a much greater offence both againſt the Blood of Chriſt, to queſtion its infinit worth, and againſt the infinitneſs and Immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of this worth, to charge it with ſom Emtineſs, which any reiteration should fill up. Therefore as the Expiatory Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, which Chriſt offered upon the Croſs, was infinitly able to do at once whatever an infinit number of other Sacrifices had bin able to do, either all together at one time, or each of them ſeverally during the ſucceſſion of all Ages; the Offering of it muſt needs be one only: and the Reiteration of it were not only ſuperfluous as to its real effect, but alſo moſt injurious to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40360:47"/>Chriſt in the very thought and Attemt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nevertheleſs this Sacrifice which by a <hi>real Oblation</hi> was not to be offered more then once, is by an Euchariſtical and devout Commemoration to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up every day. This is what the Apoſtle calls, <hi>to ſet forth the death of the Lord;</hi> to ſet it forth I ſay as well before the Eyes of God his Father, as before the Eyes of all Men: and what <hi>S.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin did explain, when he ſaid that the holy Flesh of Jeſus Chriſt was offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in three manners; by <hi>prefiguring Sacrifices</hi> under the Law, before his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the World: in <hi>real deed</hi> upon the Croſs: and by a <hi>Commemorative Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,</hi> after he is aſcended into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. All comes to this firſt, that the Sacrifice, as tis it ſelf and in it ſelf, it can never be reiterated; yet by way of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Celebration and Remembrance it may nevertheleſs be reiterated every day. Secondly, that whereas the Holy Euchariſt is by it ſelf a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> wherein God offers unto all men the Bleſſings merited by the Oblation of his Son; it likewiſe becomes by our Remembrance, a kind of <hi>Sacrifice</hi> alſo; whereby, to obtain at his hands the ſame Bleſſings, we preſent and expoſe before his Eyes that ſame holy and precious Oblation once offered. Thus the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40360:47"/>Iſraelites did continually repreſent in their Solemn Prayers to God, that Covenant which he had made once with Abraham, Iſaac and Jacob their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers. Thus did the Jews in their Captivity turn their Faces towards ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Country or the Temple where the Mercy Seat and the Ark were, which were the Memorial of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and the Sacramental Engagement of his Bleſſings. And thus the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in their Prayers do every day inſiſt upon, and repreſent to God the Father the meritorious Paſſion of their Savior, as the only ſure ground, whereon both God may give, and they obtain the Bleſſings, which they do pray for. Now, neither the Iſraelites had ever Temple or Ark or Mercy ſeat, nor the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have any Ordinance, Devotion or Myſtery, that may prove to be ſuch a bleſſed and effectual Inſtrument to reach to this Everlaſting Sacrifice, and to ſet it out ſo ſolemnly before the Eyes of God Almighty, as the Holy Euchariſt is. <hi>To men</hi> it is a ſacred <hi>Table,</hi> where Gods Miniſter is ordered to repreſent from God his Maſter the Paſſion of his dear Son, as ſtill fresh and ſtill pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful for their Eternal Salvation: <hi>and to God</hi> it is an <hi>Altar</hi> whereon Men myſtically preſent to him the ſame Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40360:48"/>as ſtill bleeding and ſtill ſueing for Expiation and Mercy. And becauſe it is the high Prieſt himſelf, the true A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed of the Lord, who hath ſet up moſt expreſsly both this Table and this Altar for theſe two ends, namely for the Communication of his Body and Blood to Men, and for the Repreſentation and Memorial of both to God; it cannot be doubted, but that the one muſt be moſt advantageous to the penitent Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and the other moſt acceptable to that good and gracious Father, who is alwaies pleaſed in his Son, and who loves of himſelf the repenting and the ſincere return of his Children. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.22.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Hence one may ſee both the great uſe and advantage of more frequent Communion: and how much it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns us, whenſoever we go to receive it, to lay out all our wants, and pour out all our Grief, our Prayers, and our Praiſes before the Lord in ſo happy a conjuncture. The primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did it ſo, who did as ſeldom meet to preach or pray, without a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, as did the old Iſraelites, to worship without a Sacrifice. On ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn daies eſpecially, or upon great Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies they ever uſed this help of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental Oblation as the moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40360:48"/>Means the Church had to ſtrengthen their Supplications, to open the Gates of Heaven, and to force in a manner God and his Chriſt to have compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on them. The People of Iſrael for the better performance of Prayer and Devotion went up to the Tabernacle and the Temple, becauſe (beſides other Motives) both theſe were Figures of that Body which was to be ſacrificed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Chriſt calls his Body <hi>this Temple. Joh.</hi> 2.19. and the firſt Chriſtians went up to their Churches, there to meet with theſe Myſteries, which do repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him both as already ſacrificed, and yet as in ſome ſort offering and giving up himſelf. Thoſe in worshipping ever turned their Eyes, their Hearts, their hopes towards that <hi>Altar</hi> and Sacrifice, whence the High Prieſt was to carry the Blood into the <hi>Sanctuary:</hi> and theſe looking toward the Croſs and their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Savior there, through his Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings hope for a way towards Heaven; being encouraged to this hope by the very <hi>Memorial,</hi> which they both take to themſelves and shew to God of theſe Sufferings. Laſtly, Jeſus our Eternal Prieſt, being from the Croſs, where he ſuffered without the Gate, gon up into the true Sanctuary which is Heaven, there above doth continually preſent
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40360:49"/>both his Body in <hi>true reality,</hi> and us as Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron did the twelve Tribes of Iſrael in a <hi>Memorial, Exod.</hi> 28.29. and on the other ſide we beneath in the Church preſent to God his Body and Blood in a <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial,</hi> that under this shadow of his Croſs, and image of his Sacrifice, we may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent our ſelves before him in very deed and <hi>reality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>O Lord who ſeeſt nothing in me, that is truely mine, but Duſt and Ashes, and which is worſe, ſinful fleſh, and Blood; look upon what I have of thee, ſome ſmall Remnant of thine I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, ſome ſmall beginnings of thy Grace, and ſome light ſparks of thy Spirit. But becauſe all theſe are defective, ſupply them, O Lord, with thy mercy, and with the Sacrifice of thy Son. Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but to thy Name, and thine Anointed give
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40360:49"/>the praiſe. Turn thine Eyes, O Merciful Father, to the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Interceſſion of thy Son, who now ſits at thy Right Hand: to the Seals of thy Covenant, which lye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee upon this Table: and to all the wants and diſtreſſes, which alſo thou ſeeſt in my heart. O Father, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify thy Son whom thou haſt ſent into this World: O Son bleſs thou this Sacrament which thou haſt ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thy Church, and ſend with it ſome influence of that Spirit whom thou haſt promiſed to all Fleſh: that by the help of theſe Mercies, the World, the Church, our Fleſh and Souls may glorify thee now and ever Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:40360:50"/>
               <head>SECTION VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning the Sacrifice of our own Perſons.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. IT is either the Error, or the incogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy of too many Chriſtians, which makes them ſomtimes beleive and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tener live, as if under the Goſpel there were no other Sacrifice but that of Chriſt upon the Croſs. It is very true indeed there is no other, nor can there be any other ſufficient, and proper for this end, of <hi>ſatisfiing</hi> Gods Juſtice, and <hi>expiating</hi> our ſins. <hi>I have troden the Winepreſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and of the People there was none with me; I looked and there was none to help.</hi> Eſay. 63.3.5. In this reſpect, tho the whole Church should in a Body, offer up her ſelf as a burnt Sacrifice to God, yet could she not contribute more, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the bearing up or bearing away <hi>the wrath to come,</hi> then all thoſe Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſouls, who ſtood neer Jeſus Chriſt when he gave up the Ghoſt, did towards the darkning of the Sun, or the shaking of the whole Earth. But that which is not ſo much as uſeful, much leſs <hi>neceſſary</hi> to this Eternal Sacrifice, which alone could <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem</hi> Mankind, is indiſpenſably both ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and uſeful, that we may have a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40360:50"/>share in this <hi>Redemtion.</hi> So that if the Sacrifice of our ſelves, which we ought to offer up to God, cannot <hi>procure</hi> Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; it is abſolutely neceſſary to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As the old Law never introduced Aaron officiating before the Lord, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole People of Iſrael, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented both by the twelve ſtones on his Ephod and the two other on his should<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Exod. 28.12.30. The Goſpel moſt commonly deſcribes Jeſus Chriſt and his Church, not only as two Parties, that do nothing the one without the other, but ſomtimes alſo as one Perſon alone: as particularly, 1. Cor. 12.12. Chriſt acts, officiates and ſuffers for his Body, in that manner that doth become the Head: and the Church imitates and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows all the motions and ſufferings of this heavenly and holy Head, in ſuch a manner as is poſſible to its weak Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The main if not the whole Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of S. Paul as well in point of faith, as of Chriſtian life, runs upon this <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> both of actions and ſufferings: And that of S. Iohn likewiſe upon this ſame <hi>Communion.</hi> The truth is, Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior had neither Birth nor Death nor Reſurrection here on Earth, but ſuch as we ought to <hi>conform</hi> us to: as he hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40360:51"/>Aſcention, nor Throne, nor Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, nor Glory, but ſuch as we may alſo have in Heaven <hi>common</hi> with him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This <hi>Conformity</hi> or likeneſs to Chriſt, which (as the Hebrewes uſe to ſpake,) is <hi>the foundation and Pillar,</hi> that is, the grand Principle of the whole Chriſtian inſtitution, relates more directly to our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty about his <hi>Sufferings;</hi> and then to our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs about his <hi>Exaltation.</hi> And the <hi>Communion,</hi> which is the other great fundamental, that S. Iohn hath ſtill in his Mouth, points more at this, and preſuppoſes that: And both make up a full Comment upon the words which our Savior ſo often commanded his Diſciples, <hi>to follow him;</hi> thereby ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifiing both the Labor, and the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of this moſt Important <hi>Journy,</hi> for without doubt we shall follow him into Heaven, if we will follow him here on Earth: and we shall have <hi>Communion</hi> with him in his <hi>Glory,</hi> if we will keep <hi>Conformity</hi> with him here in his <hi>Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Theſe three expreſſions to <hi>Follow,</hi> to be like or have <hi>Conformity,</hi> and to have <hi>Communion,</hi> which are the moſt eſſential Clauſes in the charter and charge of chriſtianity, are not to be limited to the imitation of Chriſts Moralls on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:40360:51"/>as when he bids us <hi>be Holy as he is Holy, &amp;c.</hi> but they oblige all his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to follow and imitate him likewiſe, as much as in them lies, throughout all the other parts of his life, and the very functions of his Offices. For we muſt be regenerated in his Birth, dye on his Croſs, be buried in his Grave, bear his shame in his Tribulations; in a word, Chriſt and Chriſtians are and muſt be continually together, <hi>Where I am there my ſervant shall be alſo. Ioh.</hi> 12.26. But of all theſe Duties the moſt funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental and moſt indiſpenſable, is that of bearing part of his <hi>Croſs</hi> and dying with him in <hi>Sacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Never did the Son of God intend any more to offer himſelf for his people, without his people, Then did the High Preiſts of the Law to offer themſelves for Iſrael without his Ephod, the memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of them. Chriſt preſented himſelf to God, in this great Temple, which is the world, at the head of whole Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as did the firſt born of Egypt, who alſo did prefigurate him every one in his houſe, at the head of his family. He came as a voluntary vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctim to the Altar, being attended on by his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who as it were with their hands laid all their ſins upon his head. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40360:52"/>as it was neceſſary, that they, who ſought for Attonement, should wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sacrifice: and that whoſoever would eſcape the deſtroyer, or other Plagues, should keep themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that houſe, where either the firſt born, or the Paſchal Lamb was deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: by the ſame neceſſity, whoſoever do pretend to Eternal Salvation, muſt needs appear within that houſe, about that Altar, and that Croſs, whereon this firſt born of every Creature, and this Eternal both Prieſt and Sacrifice was pleaſed to Offer up himſelf.</p>
               <p n="7">7. By this ſtanding and appearing at the Altar under the Law the ſinners in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed did not dye; the <hi>victim</hi> alone being burned and deſtroyed: but becauſe they laid their hands on it, when it was dying, and fell (for prayer and worship) on their faces down to the ground, when it did fall bleeding to death, They were as well as the very victim, repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Offer</hi> up themſelves. So the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Chriſtians likewiſe are neither cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, nor deſtroyed in that manner, that their Maſter and Savior was: yet, 1. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they look towards, and caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon his Croſs and Sufferings, as the only means both of expiating for their Sins, and of Salvation for their Souls, 2. becauſe of the great and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40360:52"/>sharp grief, which they do ſuffer who ſincerely think on the Son of God thus dying, and which is more, thus dying only for their ſakes; which to them is as it was to the Bleſſed Virgin a <hi>ſword</hi> to pierce their hearts, and likewiſe to pierce and crucifie to death their Sins: 3. becauſe their whole Body of Sin, being by this Crucifixion, really over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtered and wounded, there remains no life in them, but what they may, and will offer up and dedicate to Gods Service; The Savior thus offering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and the ſaved ſo united to him by faith, ſo plunged both into the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of, and grief for his Sufferings, and ſo reſign'd up and conſecrated to his Will for the remnant of their life, are both accounted before God for one and the ſame <hi>Sacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. It is the ſame, firſt by <hi>Imputation,</hi> ſuch as were the firſt fruits and the <hi>Lump:</hi> Rom. 11.16. The Eares of Corn and the Harveſt, which were both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether involved in, and made holy by <hi>one Offering.</hi> Levit. 23.10.11. In this ſenſe Jeſus Chriſt dying upon the Croſs, was made the firſt fruits of them that offer themſelves to God, that they may be ſanctified by his death and Sacrifice. <hi>If one be dead then all are dead;</hi> as he was made <hi>the firſt fruits of them that ſleep,</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:40360:53"/>that they should be quickned by his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. But ſecondly as the Lurnp or maſs may in ſome caſe either loſe or not get at all the priviledg and holineſs of the firſt <hi>fruits,</hi> (for example, a few sheaves of Corn, which the Worshippers had offered unto the Lord, could by no means ſanctify that Harveſt which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards should be eaten in the Service or in the Temple of an Idol) Two real Actions are required to make good this Imputation, and to join the Chriſtians to the Sacrifice of Chriſt their Head.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The firſt is, that they endeavor to crucify their ſinful members as really as Chriſt himſelf had his ſinleſs Body crucified. So that the feet, that before did run to Evil, the violent hands that did injure, the greedy eyes that did co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet, and all thoſe members of the Flesh, that were weapons of wickedneſs, may by this Croſs and Sacrifice be moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally bound, and in a good meaſure deſtroyed as to their Corruption. <hi>I do glory in the Croſs of Jeſus Chriſt, by which the world is crucified unto me, and I unto the world.</hi> Galat. 6.14. So Jeſus Chriſt, and his whole Church, and in this Church every true penitent Sinner being joined all together, do make up that compleat Sacrifice, which ſeems to have bin prefigurated by the Sacrifice at the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40360:53"/>conſecration of Aaron, <hi>Exod.</hi> 29.13.14. whereof the kidneyes and the fat about the Inwards, were burnt as a ſweet ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Oblation on the Altar: but all the Flesh, the Skin, the Feet, the Dung (Inſtruments and Emblems of Sin) were thrown and burnt without the Camp. For Jeſus Chriſt and his Church ſo concur together in one Oblation, that the bleſſed Savior contributes all that can go up into Heaven to pleaſe and appeaſe God: and we on our Part do contribute, but what deſerves to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved out of the way, the Corruption and ſmell of ſin. The Second neceſſary Condition to the aforeſaid Imputation (for no imputation either to life or death can be juſt without ſome real grounds to ſupport it) and to incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate us into the Sacrifice of Chriſts Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, is a ſerious reſolution of piety, and univerſal conſecrating both of our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and of all our Actions to God. <hi>I am crucified with Chriſt, that I may live to God. Now it is not I that live, but Chriſt lives in me, and the life which I now lead in the Flesh I live by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himſelf for me.</hi> Gal. 2.19. This Place muſt be ſo rendred accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the diſtinction of both the Greek Copies, and all the Oriental verſions.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40360:54"/>And this Act of the Church conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her ſelf to God, and joining her ſelf ſo to Chriſt as to make but one Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation with him, is the Myſtery repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the <hi>daily Sacrifice. Exod.</hi> 29.38. <hi>Numb.</hi> 28.3.</p>
               <p n="10">10. This Sacrifice did conſiſt of two parts. The firſt and cheifeſt was the <hi>Lamb,</hi> that did foreshew the Lamb of God: and the ſecond was the <hi>Meat and drink-Offering</hi> made of flower mingled with Oyl and Wine: all which being but an Additional thrown on the Lamb, morning and evening, was counted but for one and the ſame Sacrifice. Thoſe <hi>Secondary Oblations</hi> ſo thrown and burnt upon the main Sacrifice, ſignified properly theſe Offerings, which Chriſtians muſt preſent to God, of themſelves, of their Goods, and of their Praiſes. From this Meat and Drink Offering which was added to more ſubſtantial Sacrifices, came the Bread and Wine to be uſed at the celebration of Chriſts Death. Which Bread in the Communion conſidered as <hi>Sacrament,</hi> ſignifies the <hi>natural,</hi> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> it repreſents the <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Body</hi> of Chriſt, that is his Church. <hi>For we that are many</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle 1 Cor. 10.17. <hi>are one Bread.</hi> To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the holy Martyr Ignatius <hi>Epiſt. Rom.</hi> being ready to be offered up by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:40360:54"/>ſaid he was the <hi>wheat</hi> of God, which was to be ground by Beaſts teeth. Soon after the Church added <hi>Oyl</hi> and <hi>Frankincenſe</hi> to <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> to make up the whole <hi>Meat Offering</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of theſe four Things. The truth is, all what we can offer upon our own account, is but ſuch an Oblation as this Meat and Drink offering of Moſes was, that cannot be preſented but by the virtue and merits of Jeſus Chriſt, who ſupports it: and that can never aſcend up to Heaven but along with the ſacred ſmoke of that great Burnt Sacrifice, which is to carry it up thither. For on the one ſide our own perſons, our works, or any thing elſe that may be ours, are by themſelves but weak, unſubſtantial kinds of Offerings, which cannot be preſented unto God, otherwiſe but as theſe Additional Oblations, which from themſelves fall to the ground; unleſs a more ſolid Sacrifice do ſuſtain them: And on the other ſide, this ſolid and fundamental Sacrifice upholds, ſaves and ſanctifies, but thoſe perſons and things, that according to the Law of Moſes his Meat Offerings, are thrown into this his fire, are hallowed upon his Altar, and are together with him conſecrated to God by him.</p>
               <p n="11">11. For this cauſe it is, that as ſoon
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40360:55"/>as the Prophet had preached the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Everlaſting Sacrifice, and the propitiation and happineſs, which it would ſpread over all the world; he foretels at the ſame time, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and their ſucceſſors: (whom he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns by expreſſions proper to that Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomy, under which he did live) should bring the Nations from all parts of the Earth, as <hi>an Offering unto the Lord.</hi> Eſay. 66. And to the ſame purpoſe St. Paul himſelf ſpeaks of his Evangelical Office as of a Sacrificing <hi>Prieſthood;</hi> and of the Gentiles, whom he did convert to Chriſt, as of ſo many <hi>Sacrifices</hi> which he preſented to the Lord. <hi>I exerciſe,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>in the Goſpel a holy Sacerdotal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> (for the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies both) <hi>that the Oblation of the Gentiles may be acceptable, being ſanctified by the holy ſpirit. Rom.</hi> 15.16. Hence proceeds that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, which he obſerves moſt conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, never to preach the Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, without inviting preſently the Beleivers to <hi>Offer</hi> up unto God, either their Bodies and Souls: as <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. or their works of holineſs, of Praiſe, of Charity, &amp;c. as every where elſe. And theſe are the Spiritual Offerings which every true Chriſtian muſt join to caſt upon the fundamental Sacrifice of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:40360:55"/> 12. We know indeed that the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Aſſembly of Chriſtians could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver meet at the ſame time, or place, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to follow Chriſt in a Body, when he went to offer himſelf for them; or to fall upon their faces and proſtrate themſelves to the ground, when he bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his head under their Sins: Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that ſcatters men up and down throughout all places and times of the world, permitting no poſſibility of ſuch a general meeting. But the Sacrifice of Chriſt, tho it was confined to few hours and to a ſmall parcel of Ground as to the <hi>Suffering;</hi> yet being everlaſting, infinit, and ſtill the ſame, as <hi>as to the ſufficiency and virtue of it,</hi> coextends it ſelf moſt perfectly to all both times and places, when and where thoſe ſcattered members, will ever come to Offer up themſelves to God with their head. And beſides this, the ſecond part of his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotal Office, which conſiſts in <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding,</hi> continuing ſtill <hi>in the very Act,</hi> till the worlds end; They that could not embrace his Croſs, and join with him at that ſame time that he <hi>Offer'd</hi> himſelf, may do it every day, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves like poor victims loaden with ſins and miſeries, at the ſame time, that now he continues ſtill actually <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding.</hi> So in all Places, at all times,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40360:56"/>and upon any emergencies, whenſoever the Beleivers will preſent themſelves unto God, both with and by his Son Jeſus, they may ſtill receive the favor of acceptation, and that real efflux of ſaving Odor from Chriſt, which was repreſented by that typical holineſs, which the additional Oblation did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from the principal Sacrifice, when it was adjoined to it. Whereas it is moſt certain, that all the Merit and blood of Chriſt shall no more ſave Men that will not draw neer and join themſelves to conformity and Communion of his Death; then the continual and other burning Sacrifices, were ever able to conſecrate, that meat, that Wine, that Oyl, and that Frankincenſe, which were not brought, nor burned upon the the ſame Altar with them.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Now tho all men be called to this conformity and Communion in the Sufferings of Chriſt, from the time of thoſe ſufferings, until there be no times at all: and altho the daies of our preſent life, have all the priviledg which theſe ſeven feaſt daies once had, when every one might gird his loins, eat his unleavened bread, and kill his own Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock, as the Prieſt did Sacrifice the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Lamb; (which Bullock was ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added to the Paſchal Lamb, that both
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40360:56"/>might better ſuffice for the 7 Feſtival daies, beſides its other ritual and figurative im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance as a Sacrifice:) it is certain, nevertheleſs that there are two more ſpecial and extraordinary daies, wherein Chriſtians are invited by more urgent and proper Circumſtances, to preſent their Souls and Bodies by way of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Offering upon the Sacrifice of their Savior. The firſt is paſt, and that was when the Savior offered himſelf to death: when Heaven and Earth, Temple and Graves shook at the blow that killed him; when pious Souls either ſtood im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable as the bleſſed Virgin hard by his Croſs, or in a manner crucified themſelves, beating their breaſts as the Daughters of Jeruſalem: and when eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Diſciple might by the very conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of all the things he ſaw, be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſay as Thomas, <hi>let us go and let us dy with him. Joh.</hi> 11.16. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time moſt favorable and proper, next to that of his real Paſſion, is that of the holy Communion; which, as it hath bin
<note n="*" place="bottom">Gelaſ. Cyzic. part. 2. cap. 31.</note> explained, is a Sacramental Paſſion, where tho the Body be broken, and the blood shed but by way of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative Myſtery,</hi> yet both are as effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, and as truly offered for our own uſe, if we go to it worthily, as when
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40360:57"/>that holy and divine Lamb did offer himſelf the firſt time.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Therefore whenſoever Chriſtians approach to this dreadful Myſtery, and to the Lamb of God <hi>lying and ſacrificed</hi> (as ſome ſay that the holy Nicene Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil ſpeaks) <hi>upon the holy Table;</hi> it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns their main intereſt in point of Salvation, as well as in other duties, to take a ſpecial care, not to lame, and deprive the grand Sacrifice of its own due Attendance. But to behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in that manner, that, as both the principal and additional Sacrifices, were conſumed by the ſame fire, and went up towards Heaven in the ſame flame; So Jeſus Chriſt and all his Members, may jointly appear before God: this in a Sacramental Myſtery, theſe with their real Bodies and Souls, offering them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at the ſame time, in the ſame place, and by the ſame Oblation. So that whoſoever are attending on this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, ſince they do it in remembrance of their Savior, once <hi>really</hi> dead, and every day <hi>Sacramentally</hi> dying for them (do this in remembrance of me) they do it in ſuch a manner, 1. as may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come faithful Diſciples, who are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to dy both for and with their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: 2. as true and ſincere Members that cannot outlive their own head;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:40360:57"/>and 3. as truly penitent ſinners who dare not look for any share in the Glory, and Redemtion, and ſeſſion at the right or left hand of their Savior, unleſs after their way they undergo the ſame <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they will drink the ſame Cup: and unleſs they enter really into the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of that Sacrifice and thoſe Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, which their Maſter, their head, and their Savior hath paſſed through, and which this very Sacrament engages them to.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Now, this <hi>Communion</hi> doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, firſt a <hi>Conformity of Actions,</hi> that may in ſome ſort correſpond to all what Chriſt hath done as <hi>Prieſt:</hi> Secondly another <hi>Conformity of mortifications,</hi> and paſſions, that may likewiſe anſwer to whatſoever he hath Suffered as a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary <hi>Victim.</hi> As <hi>Prieſt;</hi> (for in this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion all Chriſtians after the example of their Savior, become Prieſts, ſince they offer themſelves to God) to follow all the ſteps, and take upon them all the preparations, the Courſe of life and the like diſpoſitions of mind, which were ſeen in this Bleſſed Melchiſedeck, when he preſented himſelf to God. To this effect the faithful Worshipper, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Soul and Body, which God fitted him with at his coming into this world, will lay them down at the Altar.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:40360:58"/>
               <p> Lo I come, <hi>if this Soul and Body may be uſeful to any thing,</hi> here they are both to do thy will O God.
<note n="*" place="bottom">Heb. 10.5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>And hereafter if it pleaſe thee, to uſe that power which thou haſt, as Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor over Duſt and Ashes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver weak flesh and Blood, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a brittle veſſel of Clay, over the work of thine own hands; Lo here they are to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer alſo thy good pleaſure. I do now protest to my God, that if he pleaſe to afflict me either with pain or dishonor,</hi> I will humble my ſelf <hi>under it,</hi> and be obedient unto death, even unto the death of the Croſs.
<note n="†" place="bottom">Phil. 2.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Whatſoever may happen to me either from the Jews, or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, from my Neighbors, or from strangers, ſince it is my
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40360:58"/>God that emploies them, tho they neither know, nor think it ſo; unleſs at the ſame time God help me to ſome lawful means of ſecuring my ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wrongs. I will not hereafter</hi> open my mouth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, <hi>who doth ſtrike me, except only to</hi> ſing the Pſalm, <hi>after I have eaten ſome bitter Herbs that belong to this</hi> Paſsover; <hi>and</hi> to bleſs <hi>the Lord who gave them me; and</hi> intreat <hi>him for the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who perhaps hath malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly gathered them. Hereafter no man can take away any thing from me, no life, no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, no Eſtate, ſince I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of my ſelf to lay them down, aſſoon as I can perceive that God requires them at my hands. Nevertheleſs,</hi> O Father, if thou
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40360:59"/>be willing, remove this Cup from me; <hi>yet if I must drink it,</hi> thy will be don. <hi>What kind ſoever of Suffering hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may trouble my Flesh, or what kind ſoever of Agonies may perhaps worſe trouble my Spirit, following the example of this high Prieſt, in the midſt of his bittereſt pains,</hi> O Father, into thy hand
<note n="b" place="bottom">Luke 23.46.</note> 
                  <hi>I will ever remit my life, and the dearest concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that attend it. And if thou be pleaſed, that either I live yet a while, or not; I will with my Savior</hi> bow down my head,
<note n="c" place="bottom">Joh. 19.30. Joh. 19.46.</note> 
                  <hi>I will adore thee under my burthen, and humble my ſelf under thy hand; I will give up all what thou wilt be pleaſed to ask, Goods, Joys, &amp;c. until at laſt</hi> I ſurrender and give up the Ghoſt.</p>
               <note n="a" place="bottom">Luke 22.42. Matth. 26.42.</note>
               <p n="16">
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:40360:59"/> 16. To this firſt part of our <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> with Chriſt as <hi>Prieſt,</hi> muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, whatſoever we read he did from his laſt Paſſover to his Paſſion, as far as we can imitate it: as when he washed the feet of his Diſciples: when he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his Murderers: when he received with a mild reply the rashneſs of him that ſtruck him, commiting all the reſt to God: when he took that charitable care of gently reſtoring the Ear to an inſolent fellow named Malchus: when his diſmalleſt Agonies never kept him from comforting a Penitent, <hi>this day shalt thou be with me in Paradiſe;</hi> Luk. 23.43. nor from inſtructing Good pious Souls, <hi>ye Doughters of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem weep not,</hi> &amp;c. nor from interce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for his cruelleſt Enemies, <hi>Father forgive them for they know not what they do.</hi> nor from taking care for his Relations, <hi>woman behold thy ſon</hi> &amp;c. Ioh. 19.26. Hereupon the ſucceſs of theſe both Active and Paſſive diſpoſitions muſt needs be this, that God <hi>looking</hi> firſt to <hi>Abel,</hi> and finding him endued with that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of humility, of Charity, of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of patience, <hi>which was alſo in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Phil. 2.5, he certainely will be pleaſed to <hi>look</hi> alſo upon his <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> Geneſ. 4.4.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Beſides this firſt Conformity of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40360:60"/>holy Diſpoſitions, and as it were <hi>Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotal Ornaments,</hi> between Jeſus and his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> conſidered as they are <hi>Prieſts:</hi> there muſt needs be alſo a conformity of Death and Paſſion between them, being conſidered as <hi>Sacrifices.</hi> The firſt <hi>Conformity,</hi> which regards Perſonal and Prieſtly Endowments, is never ſo exact, nor ſo full, as to adorn inferior Prieſts with all the proper Attire of Aaron; his Golden <hi>Plate,</hi> his embroidered <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phod,</hi> or his <hi>Miter,</hi> or his <hi>Breaſt Plate:</hi> yet it is never ſo defective, but that he and they may without indecency, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the inequality of their <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> officiate at one <hi>Altar.</hi> The ſecond Conformity which regards the <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> is yet much shorter then the firſt, being between things, not only unequal in degrees of perfection, but different in their nature. For really the Sacrifice of a living Creature, as the Lamb was, could not differ ſo much in nature from dead and inanimate Offerings, ſuch as the Meal, the Oil, and the Wine were, which as ſecondary Sacrifices were added to the firſt; as the Sacrifice of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt differs from what poor Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, either are in their nature, or can offer up to God in Sacrifice. For of theſe two Sacrifices as to their proper conditions, The one is Divine, all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:40360:60"/>and all Holy; and the other is human, infirm, and ſinful. And as to their ſeveral ends, The one is made to procure and work Expiation, and the other only to get ſome capacity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it. The firſt and prime Sacrifice imparts to the ſecond its Righteouſneſs; and the ſecond is thrown upon the firſt as a burthen, only to charge it with all its ſins. Nevertheleſs as under the Law, the <hi>Lamb,</hi> and the <hi>Oblation</hi> added to it, did join in one Sacrifice, becauſe both were offered upon one Altar, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by one fire: ſo under the Goſpel Chriſt and his People are accounted for one Oblation, when both in their own proper way are conſecrated by the ſame Croſs, and are in ſome manner alike obedient to death. <hi>For we have bin planted together in the likeneſs of his death, knowing this that our Old Man is dead,</hi> &amp;c. Rom. 6.5, 6.</p>
               <p n="18">18. By this likeneſs or conformity of Sufferings Chriſt is dead once to ſatisfie the rigor of the Law, and ſo muſt Chriſtians deſtroy their ſins and mortifie themſelves, that they may obſerve hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of the Goſpel. Chriſt during that terrible ſtorm that made him weep and cry aloud. Matt. 27.46.50. Luk. 23.46. Heb. 5.7. did ſuffer ſuch a heavy punishment as might
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:40360:61"/>ſatisfy Gods Juſtice: And his Myſtical Body muſt every day both undertake and ſuffer ſuch fatherly Corrections as may overmaſter their own ſins. In a word, the Holy Savior was willing to be crucified, becauſe this diſmal execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was indiſpenſably neceſſary to turn away the wrath to come: and his true members muſt be willing to crucifie themſelves with him, becauſe this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline is as indiſpenſably neceſſary to deſtroy in them by degrees that inward corruption which would bring back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain this wrath.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>O Father of Mercies I beſeech thee, both by the merits of thy Son, who now intercedes in Heaven, awd by that bloody Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice which he hath offered on the Croſs, (whereof thou ſeeſt the Sacrament upon This Table) this Day be pleaſed to receive me into the Communion of his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and hereafter into the Communion of his Glory. Caſt
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:40360:61"/>not away from thee in diſpleaſure the Elevation of theſe hands, which I will faſten to his Croſs, ſo far as they may not offend, and which I do now ſtretch before thee with a true deſire that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after they may ſerve thee; neither deſpiſe the Sacrifice of a poor Soul, which alſo his Croſs hath wounded with the ſenſe of her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and by this wound laies it open, both to pour out her own prayers, and to gaſp after thy mercies. O God and Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow on me ſuch a meaſure of that</hi> Spirit, through <hi>which thy Son</hi> offered himſelf,
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14.</note> 
                  <hi>as may ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie for ever, the Body and Soul which now I offer; and may likewiſe help me to perform the ſervice which I do promiſe. A Spirit of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:40360:62"/>Contrition, that I may ſufficiently deteſt thoſe ſins, which did deliver my God to death: then a ſpirit of Holineſs, that I may never be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them any more then a cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied man can be temted. O let this crucified Body, which I preſent to thee for ſuch, never be untied from his Croſs, either to fall to thoſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clences, that have peirced my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors hands, or to fly up to thoſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, that have crowned his head with Thorns; or to follow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt pleaſures, that have filled his dear Soul with greif, that have filled his Entrails with Gall. Arm and Rod of the Lord, who in thine Anger didſt revenge all theſe ſins upon my Savior, in thy mercy cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and deſtroy them alſo in me. So my God accept of a heart, that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:40360:62"/>ſheds now before thee its Tears, as a poor Victim does its blood: and that raiſes up unto thee all its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, its thoughts, its zeal, as a Burnt offering doth its flames. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſince my Sacrifice can be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, holy, nor accepted, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: Accept of it, O Father, as it is an Oblation ſupported by that Sacrifice, which alone is able to pleaſe thee. Receive it clothed with the Righteouſneſs of thy Son, and made acceptable with that holy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume that riſes from of his Altar: And grant that He who ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, and they who are by him ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, may be joined in one Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and may enjoy hereafter with thee the ſame Glory.</hi> Our Father which art in Heaven, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:40360:63"/>
               <head>SECTION VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning the Oblation of our Goods and Alms, or the Sacrifice of Juſtice.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. IT is an expreſs and often repeated Law of God by Moſes, and no where repeated by Chriſt, that no wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipper shall preſume to appear before him with emty hands. Sincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt have them full at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the holy Communion, with four diſtinct ſorts of Sacrifices. 1. The Sacramental and <hi>commemorative Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> of Chriſt. 2. The real and <hi>Actual Sacrifice</hi> of themſelves. 3. The <hi>free will Offering</hi> of their Goods. 4. The <hi>Peace Offering</hi> of their Praiſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The firſt as repreſenting the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice offered on the Croſs, is the ground of the three others, eſpecially of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: which muſt no more be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from it, then Parts are from the Whole, or the Body from its Head. Theſe two are ſo cloſe coupled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that St. Auſtin
<note n="*" place="bottom">Aug. apud Fulg. de Bapt. Aethiop. c. ult.</note> more then once, by the Body of Chriſt in the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, underſtands Chriſts myſtical Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:40360:63"/>which is the Church. And St. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>St. Cypr. l.</hi> 2. <hi>Ep.</hi> 3.</note> ſaies expreſsly, that Chriſt and his People are contained and united together in the Holy Cup (that being repreſented by the Wine, this repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Water;) ſo that Chriſt is not there without his People, nor the People without their Savior.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Third and fourth, which are the Sacrifices of our Goods and of our Praiſes, are appendages following after the ſecond, that is the, Sacrifice of our own ſelves, by as natural a conſequence, as the fruits and leaves follow the Tree, and as what we <hi>have</hi> or what we <hi>can,</hi> muſt needs come after what we <hi>are.</hi> All the world know how that blemisht and lame Sacrifices were abominable under the Law: and certainly Bodies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>heads,</hi> ſouls without their <hi>faculties,</hi> and Perſons without their proper Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, are not better under the Goſpel. Such mutilated Sacrifices cannot ſuit with that of Chriſt, which was perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whole and entire. Therefore as when we once offer our ſelves to God, our Souls and Bodies, become attending Sacrifices on the Sacrifice of Jeſus Chriſt: ſo muſt by the ſame equity, all our Goods and Services, by way of ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40360:64"/>Oblations attend the Sacrifice of our Perſons. And as the <hi>Lamb,</hi> in the daily Sacrifice was never offered without its <hi>Meat Oblation,</hi> nor this meat Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without its incenſe, its Wine, its Oil: So the Eternal Son and Lamb of God, who was pleaſed to offer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for me, muſt neither be offered without me; nor whenſoever I offer up my ſelf, both by him and with him, muſt I appear as a dry and unſavory Meat offering without juice, without ſweet ſmell, without all the holy diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of readineſs and joy to obey and pleaſe my God in all good works, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Incenſe, the Wine, and the Oil, were under the Law ſacred Emblemes. In a word, whenſoever we offer our ſelves, we offer by the ſelf ſame Act, all that we have, all that we can: and ſo conſequently we do engage for all, that it shall be dedicated to the Glory of God, and that it shall be ſurrendred into his hands, employed to ſuch uſes, upon ſuch occaſions and times, as he will be pleaſed to appoint.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Hear then, <hi>my ſon</hi> (as ſaies the wiſe man) <hi>look to they feet, when thou entreſt into the houſe of God, leſt thou offer the Sacrifice of fools.</hi> Eccleſ. 5.6. It is the Sacrifice as well as the part of a fool to offer the Perſon without the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:40360:64"/>Goods that attend it, as it were the bones without the ſinewes and the flesh that cover them. It is the ſame Act of an Impious wretch to mangle, and to mutilate, either the holy Sacrifice which Jeſus hath made to his father, or the holy Sacrament which he hath ordained to his Church, or that holy Oblation, which after his Sacrifice and at his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he is pleaſed to require of us. And after we have preſented it, it is an Act, not only of great Impiety, but of as great a Sacriledg, as was that of Anani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, to withdraw without leave, any <hi>part</hi> of that Whole which we have devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Gods Service.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It behoves not Iſrael alone to go forth out of Egypt with all their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Cattle, and Goods, to offer them unto the Lord, that he may take either all, or ſuch a part, as he will be pleaſed to chuſe; Exod. 10.25, 26. All the Gentiles were likewiſe to go and give themſelves up to Gods ſervice with their Gold, their Silver, their Drome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries, and their Chariots loden with their cheifeſt ſubſtance: The Egyptians with all their wealth: Tyre and Sidon with their Merchandiſe: Eſay. 23.18. and 60.6, 7, 9. The wiſe men with their Frankincenſe, their Myrrh and their Gold: and ſo every ſinner at his
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:40360:65"/>Converſion to God, was to conſecrate all to Jeſus Chriſt, and to the ſervice of his Church. From that very moment, that by any reall Act of converſion, of faith, of repentance, or of vow, we have given up our ſelves to Chriſt, who hath likewiſe given himſelf for us; as by virtue of this mutual Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all what he poſſeſſes becomes ours, namely his Grace, his Immortality, his Glory; and ſo he beſtowes it upon us, according to the times, and degrees which he ſees beſt for our <hi>Salvation:</hi> by the ſame conſequence, all whatſoever we have doth become his, ſo that he may take it after in what proportion and ſeaſon ſoever he shall ſee beſt for his <hi>Glory.</hi> The two Aſſes which he ſent for by his diſciples, that he might ride on them to Jeruſalem, and the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber which he commanded to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that he might eat the Paſſover in it, were not ſo abſolutely his, as are our lives, our Goods, &amp;c. whenſoever <hi>the Lord hath need of them:</hi> Matt. 21.2, 3. Luk. 22.11. Thoſe things were his only by the Right of propriety, which, as to a Soveraign Lord and God, is naturally reſerved upon any thing which he creates or ſaves; but theſe are his beſides, becauſe we with our ſelves have given them. When he
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:40360:65"/>calls for the former, to deny them were injuſtice, but to deny theſe latter, were a viſible Sacriledg: all what we are, what we can do, and what we can give, even to the leaſt veſſel in our houſes, being involved and made holy, in this one Conſecration. <hi>In that day shall there be upon the very Bridles of the Horſes holineſs unto the Lord: and every pot in Jeruſalem and Juda shall be holy unto the Lord.</hi> Zechar. 14.20, 21.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This Conſecration whereby the worshipper offers and reſigns up all him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and all his Concernments to God, if it be well don, and duly performed, is, firſt as for our Souls and Bodies a Chriſtian <hi>Apotheoſis,</hi> if I may uſe this word, which both makes them capable of the Sacrifice and grace of Chriſt, and raiſes and prefers them to the very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that is the Condition of holineſs and Immortality of God. Secondly as to the Conſecrated things; it is a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous priviledg, which in the end in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitly multiplies every thing, which is thus parted with; it bleſſes the uſe of it altho it be but preſented, as long as we can enjoy it, and finally exchanges it, when we can enjoy it no more, for ſuch advantagious returnes, as may be conceived to be, not ſuch as when water was turned into Wine, or dirt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:40360:66"/>into Gold, but ſuch, as if we conceive a glaſs of water, turned into ſtreams of Everlaſting Comſorts, the duſt of Iſrael into ſo many ſtars of Heaven, ſmall Cottages of Clay into Royal Palaces; and vain declining shadows into real and Eternal poſſeſſions: <hi>Thou haſt bin faithful in a few things, I will make thee Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler over many things,</hi> &amp;c. Matth. 25.21. But if the Law of theſe Conſecrations be not well performed; if <hi>Levi</hi> come to ſerve <hi>Ashtaroth,</hi> after he hath dedicated himſelf to God; and if the Offerings of the People, be employed to profane uſes after they have toucht Gods Altar; then there are as many and as heavy Curſes to be lookt for, as on the other ſide upon a better uſe, there are many and great Bleſſings to be expected. So that upon all conſiderations, both of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and of Duty; firſt we muſt give up all to God: next after we have given we muſt fly all, not only as two moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious ſins, but alſo as two moſt terrible miſcheifs, the <hi>Sacriledg</hi> in withdrawing at any time when God demands it, what hath bin thus conſecrated to him: and the <hi>Profaneneſs</hi> in miſpending upon ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, or worſe uſes, what of it he is pleaſed to allow to our proper ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, and other lawfull Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:40360:66"/> 7. Now tho Chriſt our bleſſed Savior, by that everlaſting and ever ſame Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of himſelf, offer himſelf virtually up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions: and we on our ſide, alſo offer our ſelves, and what is ours, with him ſeveral other waies, beſides that of the holy Communion: as at our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and firſt Act of faith in him, Chriſt (ſaies St. Auſtin,)
<note n="a" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Aug. Evang. Queſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 33.</note> 
                  <hi>is ſacrificed for the ſalvation of every ſinner, at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moment he repents and beleives him to have bin Sacrificed;</hi> and at our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, <hi>For every one offers the Sacrifice of the Paſſion of the Lord, at that time, that he is conſecrated by the faith of this Paſſion, and baptiſed a Chriſtian,</hi> ſaith the ſame fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<note n="b" place="bottom">Auguſt. Expoſ. incheat. ad Rom.</note> and the <hi>Baptiſm of Chriſt is the blood of Chriſt,</hi> ſaith another.
<note n="c" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ. Hom.</hi> 10. <hi>Heir.</hi>
                  </note> Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs becauſe Chriſt offers himſelf for us at the holy Communion in a more ſolemn and public ſacramental way; (thence it comes, that the Memorial of the ſacrifice of Chriſt thereby celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, takes commonly the Name of the Sacrifice it ſelf, as St. Auſtin
<note n="d" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Aug. de Civ. c.</hi> 5. <hi>id. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p.</hi> 23. <hi>ad Boniſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Conſert, Diſp.</hi> 2, <hi>hoc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt.</hi>
                  </note> explains it often) we are then obliged in a more ſpecial manner, to renew all our Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, all the vows of our Baptiſm, all the firſt fruits of our Converſion, and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:40360:67"/>all the particular promiſes, which it may be we have made, either at our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting of ſome ſin, or at our delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from ſome eminent danger, or at the recovery out of ſome greivous ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or at the receiving ſome other ſignal mercy, whether for our ſelves, or for our friends. <hi>I will go into thy houſe with burnt offerings, I will pay thee my vows, which my lips have uttered, and my mouth hath ſpoken, when I was in trouble.</hi> Pſal. 67.13.14. Then and there at the Altar of God muſt we, both diſcharge all the vows, which for ſome hindrance or other, we had not yet the Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to fulfil; and ſet afresh from <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> to <hi>communion,</hi> as they did the <hi>Shew-loaves</hi> from <hi>Sabbath</hi> to <hi>Sabbath,</hi> all thoſe other Performances, which by their nature, and our duty, can never be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, but with the very end of our daies.</p>
               <p n="8">8. So shall the new Iſrael tread on the pious ſteps of the Old, who ever from time to time reiterated, either in <hi>Miſpah,</hi> or in <hi>Gilgal,</hi> &amp;c. that Covenant which the Lord had made with him in <hi>Sinai.</hi> It is true, the Lord did not then again repeat the Thunder, that once made the Mountains tremble; as in our Churches he doth not reiterate that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Paſſion, that made the powers of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:40360:67"/>Heaven mourn and shake: Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs as Joſuah, Aſa, Joſias, Jehojadah, and other ſuch holy men, could from their Maſter aſſure the People, that the Covenant which they did renew, for example, <hi>in Shechem,</hi> Joſ. 24.25. 2 Chr. 15.12. and 23.16. was not leſs power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, either to bleſs the obſervers, or to deſtroy the offenders thereof, then it was when Moſes, and the Holy Angels publisht it at the firſt upon <hi>Sinai:</hi> So now the Miniſters of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, having in their hands the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Goſpel, (true Seals and Tables of the new Law) may both pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and give them out as Evidences; that the ſacrifice of their Maſter is not leſs able to ſave mens Souls, when it is offered to men, and Sacramentally offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again to God, at the holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, then when it was newly offered upon the Croſs. And this is the reaſon, wherefore all faithful Chriſtians ought then as effectually to reinforce all their Oblations, their vows, their Contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and their proteſtations, <hi>Men and Brethren what shall we do? And God forbid that I should ever glory but in the Croſs of my Savior;</hi> as the Iſraelites did by proteſting upon the like occaſions, <hi>We will obey the Lord our God and the Lord is the God, the Lord is the God.</hi>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:40360:68"/>1 King. 18.39. both Iſraelites and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſeconding their Proteſtation of obedience, and their proſtrations of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and reſignations of their minds, with ſecondary ſacrifices: thoſe of <hi>Bulls</hi> and <hi>Rams;</hi> theſe of <hi>Alms and Pious works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. By this it is eaſie to ſee, that our holy Euchariſtical Communions are much correſpondent to thoſe Feaſts, that did call the People of Iſrael toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, firſt to appear and proſtrate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before the Lord with <hi>ſacrifices for their ſin:</hi> and then to lay upon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar that other kind of Sacrifices which they uſed to call
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Peace offerings, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Peace Offerings,</hi> and which were ordained to expreſs both their thankfulneſs to God, and their Charity to men. And in this friendly concurrence both of Myſteries, and of holy duties that attend them, all reſpects duly obſerved, Moſes may ſtill with the ſame power command both new and old Iſrael, <hi>thou shalt keep the feaſt unto the Lord thy God, with a Tribute of a free will offering of thine hand which thou shalt give unto the Lord thy God, according as the Lord thy God hath bleſſed thee: And thou shalt rejoyce before the Lord thy God, thou and thy Son and thy Daughter, the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:40360:68"/>Levite, the ſtranger the Fatherleſs and the Widdow. And you shall not appear before the Lord emty. Every man shall give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the bleſſing of the Lord thy God which he hath given thee.</hi> Deut. 16.10, 11.</p>
               <p n="19">19. The firſt Chriſtians ever took it, and conſtantly practiſed it ſo. For when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they met at their devotions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Holy Communion was the moſt ordinary and the moſt eſſential part, they did make the uſe of all their Goods to be common among themſelves: and the diſtribution of this bleſſed <hi>Sacrament</hi> was ſo conſtantly attended by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of their <hi>Offerings,</hi> that it is ſomewhat hard to diſcern which of the two the Apoſtolical Hiſtory intends to ſignify by the <hi>Breaking of bread,</hi> ſo often mentioned in the Acts. Some pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and learned men have thought that this largeneſs and frequency of Offerings, which in the primitive times was all the ſtock they had for pious uſes, made that Article which immediatly follows that of the <hi>Church,</hi> that is, <hi>the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> or <hi>Communication of the Saints.</hi> But however tho this were not the <hi>Article of faith</hi> there meant, yet it was an Act of Piety ſo frequent, and ſo eſſential in thoſe daies, that St. Luke would place it amongſt thoſe other ſacred fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that comprehend the whole du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:40360:69"/>and ſervice of the Church. <hi>They continued ſtedfaſtly in the Doctrine of the Apoſtles and in the Communion, and in breaking of bread, and in prayer.</hi> Act. 2.24. Thus were the primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians literally and punctually ſuch as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly David had propheſied they should be, a People that would come and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelves, with their <hi>free will offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> to Chriſt, <hi>in the Day of his Power;</hi> and of that glorious effuſion of Graces, that like to a Celeſtial dew, would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear wonderful by a thick and ſudden producing of ſubjects and ſouldiers ready armed for his ſervice: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.</p>
               <p n="11">11. For this purpoſe it was that the Bishops had in their Churches, two Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. One of them was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> within that ſpace where the Miniſters did officiate at the Altar, and where were Curtins purpoſely shut to keep non-Communicants from the ſight of and acceſs to the Holy My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries. The other was where the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple could freely come to offer their Gifts, part whereof afterwards was brought by the Deacons to the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Table. Hither were brought the <hi>Free will Offerings</hi> of the People, Bread, Wine, Oil, Wooll, ſometimes Cloth, Silver, and any thing els, that might be uſeful to the Church, (till by expreſs
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:40360:69"/>Canons of the Church,
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 37. <hi>Afric.</hi>
                  </note> thoſe Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in kind were limited to ſuch things only, as could be emploied about the ſacraments and ſervice of the Church) and all this was offered up to God by all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, by way of a <hi>daily Sacrifice.</hi> And when the Chriſtians had offered up to God their Goods, the Prieſt who did receive them, did ſolemnly pray to God, that he would be pleaſed <hi>to look on their Oblations, as he did once on them of Abel, of Noah, and of Abraham.</hi> Out of theſe Oblations, the Elements of the holy Communion were taken forth and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented at the other Table, where they were bleſt by the Bishop or Prieſt, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed by him to the People as from God, to aſſure them he had accepted, of both their perſons, and offerings, and that inſtead of the Bread and Wine, which they had offered upon his Altar, as either the <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> or the <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives</hi> of all their Goods, he was pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to return to them not ſimple Bread, and ſimple Wine, but ſuch Bleſſed Bread and Wine, as were both the ſacred My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Body and Blood of his Son, and an infallible ſurety of all Things depending thereon. This is the reaſon; why, becauſe primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans never received thoſe holy Myſteries, but after they had made their Offerings;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:40360:70"/>and becauſe thoſe very Myſteries, which they <hi>received,</hi> were commonly taken, as to the matter, from that Bread and Wine, which they had before <hi>Offered;</hi> The Holy fathers, (for inſtance S. Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus)
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 30, 34. <hi>Et alibi paſſim.</hi>
                  </note> who then had no occaſion to be ſo exact, or cautious as to diſtinguish preciſely the Nature of two ſacred Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which went conſtantly together, do not ſcruple to ſpeak of the bleſſed Communion, promiſcuouſly as Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Sacrifice.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Now to bring all this more home; The Law of Antient Iſrael, the practiſe of the Primitive Church, and the very equity of the thing it ſelf, do ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently teſtify, that we ought not in theſe, more then in the former Ages, to appear before the Lord with emty hands: that it is not more fit for worshippers now then it was then, to preſent their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, without their Goods, as it were trees, without their ſap and fruit: and that theſe ſame Nations, which in the prediction of Eſay, were at their firſt coming, to bring and conſecrate both themſelves and their Gold unto the Lord, muſt not be now leſs liberal, when by their Sacrifice, they appear to renew the vowes of their former Conſecration; as ſurely God is not, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:40360:70"/>the ſame occaſions leſs merciful, when by his holy Sacrament he renews unto them the Covenant of his ſaving Grace. Therefore he that comes rich, is bound to appear before his Savior, with his hands full of ſuch free Will offerings, as he may take out of his abundance, as did in Iſrael the husbandman out of a plentiful harveſt, when the Lord had bleſſed his field. He that is leſs able, muſt offer out of what he can either get by his labor, or ſpare by his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimony: as the poor widow did, when she offered her Mite. In a word eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, whether he be rich or poor, is to lay down at the Offerings of God, according as the ſame God hath either bleſſed or ſpared him. 1. Cor. 16.2.</p>
               <p n="13">13. The quantity of theſe Oblations, whether extraordinary, as upon a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Day, or more ordinary, as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other daily occaſions, is wholy left to the diſcretion of the Chriſtian wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipper. And whereas God by his Law, did deal with the Iſraelites, as fathers do with Children in an ago unfit to guide itſelf, preſcribing to them the meaſure, the time, and the manner of every thing, which they were either to do, or to give; our Savior hath by the Goſpel freed all Chriſtians from this punctual <hi>Pedagogy,</hi> leaving them, as
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:40360:71"/>men able to give an account of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, both to their own Judgment, and to the direction of his ſpirit; But if this different way of the Goſpel diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charges Chriſtians now adaies from the ſubjection of doing punctually, and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally every thing, which the ancient Iſrael were to obſerve; it certainly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges them to do more as to the matter, and to do it in a better manner. And God forbid that this honor and liberty, which he vouchſafes us above what he did to the Jews, should be taken by us, either as a permiſſion, or as an occaſion of being worſe. Therefore God in former times did give ſpecial Laws to his People for every thing they were to do, in point either of Piety, or Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; for example, they were to give the Tenth part of whatſoever they could gather out of their <hi>feilds,</hi> their <hi>Trees</hi> and their <hi>flocks,</hi> beſides another Tenth part every third year, that is a Thirtieth part every year: and what ever could grow of it ſelf, during the vacancy of every ſeventh year: They were bound moreover to many other charitable waies of helping the poor, as to lend them mony without taking either uſe or pawn: and to leave in their fields and Vineyards ſo much of their Corn, and fruits behind, as could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:40360:71"/>the labor and diligence of many honeſt Neighbors, who, at the end of the year, had no other Harveſt then this Gleaning. And altho all this was <hi>Charity,</hi> yet it was among the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſrael called <hi>Juſtice,</hi> becauſe it was commanded by Law, and that they were obliged to pay theſe Almes, as ſtrictly as any other Debt. Here then a downright Chriſtian will do well to take notice, of what all theſe charges may come to, and what proportion they will bear with the Eſtate and revenue that God bleſſes him with, that ſo he may contribute towards works of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and Charity, not only ſo much but more; and if not in the very ſame, yet in as good a kind as the Jews did. So that he may go beyond them in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, whom the Goſpel commands us to exceed in all other virtues, as we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed them in Bleſſings.</p>
               <p n="14">14. The time of theſe oblations is not more limited then their meaſure. At firſt S. Paul had appointed the firſt day of the week, that is the <hi>Lords day,</hi> for the gathering of thoſe Charitable aſſiſtances, and, as he calls them, <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Sacrifices,</hi> 1. Cor. 16.2. Phil. 4.18. which were to be ſent to the poor Brethren of Jeruſalem; becauſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from that time, that day was in a
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:40360:72"/>more ſpecial manner conſecrated to the ſolemn Miniſtry of Prayers, of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and of <hi>Communion.</hi> Now, tho the danger of Profaneneſs, which then was leſs to be feared, hath in our daies made the uſe of this <hi>Sacrament</hi> much leſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon then that of <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Prayer.</hi> Nevertheleſs ſince by theſe two holy exerciſes, both God ſpeaks to us, and we to him; this should be warning enough, not to preſume to appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him without a Gift. And that we may both bear up the more eaſily the expenſes of this weekly Sacrifice, and diffuſe more univerſally the ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor thereof into all the parts of our life; it would be a piece of holy prudence, to take care that every day should both bear ſome part of the burthen, and have ſome share of the holineſs. And that by a daily attending to this ſervice, the Rich be ſtill induſtrious to defalk ſome larger portions of his abundance; the poor to ſteal ſome thing out of his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries: and the middle conditioned man to ſpare what he can out of all his competence. But ſpecially when the good Providence lets fall into our hand ſome conſiderable advantages, then let him that will grow rich in God, look upon thoſe temporal occaſions, as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious time of Harveſt, whereof he
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:40360:72"/>muſt be ſure to reſerve the firſt fruits to God: and let him have a place in his houſe, like the Treaſury in the Temple, where he may daily caſt in his <hi>Talent,</hi> or his <hi>Didrachm,</hi> or his <hi>Mite,</hi> according as God daily bloſſes him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and whence he muſt be ſure to take nothing, but for a ſpecial holy uſe, as if he did take it from Gods Altar.</p>
               <p n="15">15. It is true indeed that not only this, but alſo any thing elſe that we have at home, is already conſecrated, ſince God having given it to us, we have given it back again unto God. For whenſoever we gave him up our own perſons, all our Goods were involved in this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conſecration, and thereby became <hi>ipſo facto</hi> holy <hi>Offerings</hi> unto the <hi>Lord.</hi> But as theſe holy Offerings under the Law were of two ſorts, ſome which the Worshipper, and his wife, and Children might eat; ſome of which it was not lawful for any to eat, except the Prieſts only; my meaning is that the truly pious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian should gather day by day, and by little and little (both to make his Devotion leſs burthenſom, and by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual application to this work, to ſanctify the whole courſe of his life the better) a Magazine of holy things of this laſt kind, which may be only emploied to God and his Churches ſervice.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:40360:73"/> 16. But at the ſame inſtant that the Chriſtian Worshipper shall take the materials of his good works, out of this ſtore, he muſt have a great care to draw withal out of the good Treaſure of his heart the <hi>fire,</hi> and the <hi>Frankincenſe,</hi> that is, the zeal and the holy thoughts that may improve, and raiſe good <hi>moral works,</hi> to the being of <hi>Religious Sacrifices.</hi> And as without doubt, at firſt, he had a care not to lay aſide theſe firſt fruits, in a Corner of his houſe, either negligently or rudely, as ſome do throw their Alms into Beggars hands, or as Judas did his thirty Pieces into the Temple; ſo he muſt not forget himſelf ſo much, as to take them thence, and beſtow them on the Body or members of Chriſt, that is, the Church and his Neighbor, but with ſuch pious Elevations and applications of his mind, as may become both that Majeſty which he adores, and the pious and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Act, that he intends. Let him do it, whether at his door, or in the way, or in the Temple, it matters not, for the hour is long ſince come, that Religious Acts, or Worshippings, are confined nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>this Mountain, nor to Jeruſalem;</hi> Joh. 4.21. whereſoever God gives thee the occaſion and power to perform any holy work, there he makes <hi>holy Ground</hi> for thee: only this work, to be holy, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:40360:73"/>becoming a Worshipper, muſt by all means be don <hi>in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> This <hi>Spirit</hi> will teach us, what Flesh and Blood cannot do, both to perceive, and conſider, not an Angel only, as the Patriarcks often did, but Chriſt himſelf, in the condition of an afflicted Church, for example, or of an honeſt diſtreſſed friend; and then at ſuch occaſions to lay our liberalities, with that ſame mind and thought that a true Worshipper would lay his <hi>Oblations,</hi> upon the Altar, where he knows that Chriſt will moſt effectually both find it, and accept of it. Once He received the Gold the Myrrh and the Frankincenſe, which the wiſe men gave Joſeph; He did alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Goods which Suſanna, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religious Women did put in the hands of his Diſciples; ſince that time the Church and all her diſtreſſed Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers have bin inſtated by Chriſt himſelf moſt expreſsly into the Place of theſe happy Perſons; and as if they had bin for this purpoſe created Chriſts ſolemn Officers and Angels, about the time that he was to ſuffer and to leave his beloved Diſciples, he promiſed them both to accept, and account as beſtowed on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, theſe ſmall Offerings, which for his ſake we should depoſite in their hands. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.40, 45.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:40360:74"/> 17. This ſame ſpirit, and this Actual application, is the only means that we can have to raiſe up good moral works, and to make them true <hi>Heave-Offerings.</hi> Without this Elevation, what we give; may in it ſelf be a good deed, to us a conſiderable-expenſe, and to other men ſome benefit; but to God, it is no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice: or it is ſuch a ſacrifice, as ſends up no ſavor above: but either like the Oblation of Cain, falls all down to Ashes and Duſt, or like the Alms of Phariſes to ſuch a paltry toward, as we get perhaps from men. <hi>Gen.</hi> 10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="18">18. All theſe conſiderations and pious intentions of the Soul, which to the <hi>Worshipper</hi> muſt be inſtead of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotal Utenſils,</hi> and to the <hi>Oblation,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the fire and Frankincenſe, are much revived and ſtirred up by the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantial ſolemnity and Holineſs of the bleſſed <hi>Communion.</hi> Look to the Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Ancient Iſraelites. <hi>I was, &amp;c.</hi> Deut. 26.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I Dare appear before the Lord with all my ſins and my ſorrows; It is very juſt alſo, that I should appear with theſe few bleſſings, which are mine; they are mine
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:40360:74"/>by thy favor, and</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them of thy hand, now do I offer them to thee.
<note n="*" place="bottom">1 Chron. 29.14.</note> 
                  <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give I beſeech thee my</hi> ſins, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me from my</hi> ſorrows, <hi>and accept of this ſmall Bleſſing. Accept of this my ſacrifice, as thou didſt of that of Abel, of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, and of Noah; or rather look in my behalf on that only true Sacrifice, whereof here is the Sacrament; the Sacrifice of the only unſpotted Lamb: the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of thine own Son: of thine only begotten Son, of thy Son proceeding from thee, to dy for me.</hi> O let him again come from thee to me; let him come now as the only begotten of the Father full of grace and of truth to bleſs me, Amen, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:40360:75"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40360:75"/>
            <head>INDEX.</head>
            <list>
               <item>SECTION. I. <hi>The Importance of well underſtanding the Nature of this Sacrament.</hi> Pag. 1.</item>
               <item>SECTION. II. <hi>Concerning the Sacrament, as it is a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of the Sufferings and Death of Chriſt.</hi> p. 4.</item>
               <item>SECTION. III. <hi>Of the bleſſed Sacrament, as it ſtands for a Sign of preſent Graces.</hi> p. 19</item>
               <item>SECTION. IV. <hi>Concerning the Communion, as it is not a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation only, but a means of Grace.</hi> p. 36.</item>
               <item>SECTION. V. <hi>Of the Bleſſed Communion as being a Pledg of the Happineſs and Glory to come.</hi> p. 56.</item>
               <item>SECTION. VI. <hi>Of the Holy Euchariſt, as it implies a Sacrifice. And firſt of the Commemorative Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi> p. 71.</item>
               <item>SECTION. VII. <hi>Concerning the Sacrifices of our own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> p. 80.</item>
               <item>SECTION. VIII. <hi>Concerning the Oblation of our Goods and Alms, or the Sacrifice of Juſtice.</hi> p. p. 106.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
